Good afternoon, good evening, good night, wherever you are.
下午好，傍晚好，晚上好，无论你在哪里。
So today I want to talk about FaRM,
所以今天我想谈谈 FaRM ，
this is a paper from 2015,
这是一篇 2015 年的论文，
so what a little bit more of a recent paper,
是比较近的一篇论文，
and it's really a research paper,
这是一篇研究论文，
and the topic of the research paper is
这个研究论文的主题是，
trying to explore some ideas and technologies
试图探索一些想法和技术
to get high performance transactions,
来获得高性能的事务，
and with high performance,
高性能，
just to make sure we're on the, roughly what we're looking for,
为了确保我们，是我们想要的，
high performance from that means,
高性能意味着，
they're getting 140 million transactions per second,
他们获得 1.4 亿个事务每秒，
on this you know TATP benchmark, using 90 machines,
在 TATP 基准上，使用 90 台机器，
and so you know whether this number is impressive,
所以这个数字是否令人印象深刻，
of course you know depends on the numbers you know,
当然取决于你知道的数字，
and so does anybody remember,
有人还记得，
how many transactions per second Spanner could do?
Spanner 每秒能处理多少事务吗？
Anybody?
有人知道吗？
So if we remember the paper,
所以如果我们记得那篇论文，
you know certain transaction there you know took about
那里发生多少事务，
depending on what you did,
取决于你所做的，
you know 10 to 100 milliseconds,
10 到 100 毫秒，
so you know 10 to 100 transactions per second.
所以每秒 10 到 100 个事务。
So, the number transactions that FaRM can do is
所以， FaRM 可以处理的事务数量是
in a completely different order of magnitude.
在一个完全不同的数量级。
And that partly is because they're completely different systems,
部分是因为它们是完全不同的系统，
Spanner tries to do synchronous [] replication across the world,
Spanner 试图在全球范围内进行同步复制，
and FaRM actually everything runs in a single data center.
而 FaRM 的一切都在一个数据中心运行。
And so the applications that been targeted by FaRM and Spanner a quite different,
所以， FaRM 和 Spanner 针对的应用程序完全不同，
Spanner targeting applications that cannot tolerate the crash with a data center,
Spanner 针对不能容忍数据中心崩溃的应用程序，
like you know F1 AD serving database,
比如 F1 广告服务数据库，
while Spanner is much, very well,
Spanner 非常好，
FaRM much more targeting sort of
FaRM 更针对
like you're you're using MySQL
比如你是所有 MySQL
or some other sort of database application database system,
或某种其他类型的应用数据库系统，
and you want much more high performance transactions,
你想要更高性能的事务，
then you know FaRM sort of a possible design or a possible alternative.
那么 FaRM 是一种可能的设计或可能的选择。
They do provide strict serializability,
它们提供了严格的可串行化，
which is similar to the external consistency that Spanner offered.
类似于 Spanner 提供的外部一致性。
And so the whole goal is to get high performance,
所以，整个目标是获得高性能，
so there are numerous ideas you know they're going to achieving high performance.
有很多想法会实现高性能。
One, they they shard,
一个是，他们分片，
that's probably the main you know standard technique that they used,
这可能是他们使用的主要标准技术，
that was going to give us the performance,
这将给我们带来性能，
for example if you know different records are on a different shards,
例如，如果不同的记录在不同的分片上，
and transactions you know touch the different shard,
事务触及不同的分片，
then these transaction can just run in parallel,
然后这些事务可以并行运行，
and so, if you have 90 machines,
所以，如果你有 90 台机器，
you know get 90 times you know the performance of a single machine.
获得一台机器的性能的 90 倍。
So sharding are sort of starting point,
所以分片是一个起点，
but then they go much further,
但他们走得更远，
so they use non-volatile DRAM,
他们使用非易失性 DRAM ，
and this is to avoid to the bottleneck of having to write to stable storage devices,
这是为了避免不得不写入稳定存储设备的瓶颈，
so in their design,
所以在他们的设计中，
you don't actually have to write in the [critical path] to an SSD or a disk,
你不必写入关键路径到固态硬盘或磁盘，
and so they avoid the whole cost of doing so,
所以，他们避免了这样做的全部花费，
which can be quite expensive,
这可能相当昂贵，
and that's for example you think about your implementations of Raft,
例如，你可以考虑你的 Raft 实现，
you know they they store you know or make data persistent,
他们存储或者使数据持久化，
and typically you know making something persistent on a stable storage device,
通常情况下，在稳定的存储设备上进行持久化，
you know the order of hundreds of milliseconds, or hundreds of,
几百毫秒的量级，
a few milliseconds you know to tens of milliseconds to ten milliseconds,
几毫秒到十毫秒，
if you're actually using a magnetic disk,
如果你使用磁盘，
an SSD you know sort of, sort of millisecond,
一个 SSD 有几毫秒，
and so given the time for they operate,
所以，考虑到它们运作的时间，
you know that way just too costly,
这种方式花费太高了。
so they use some people they call non-volatile DRAM,
所以他们使用一些人称为非易失性 DRAM ，
this we'll talk about in a second,
我们稍后会谈到这一点，
and then so that gets rid of storage access cost.
这样就消除了存储访问成本。
And so the next two bottleneck they address is
他们要解决的下两个瓶颈是
CPU bottlenecks and network bottlenecks,
CPU 瓶颈和网络瓶颈，
and for that, to use technical called kernel bypass,
要实现这一点，需要使用一种称为内核旁路的技术，
which basically avoids the operating system for, to talk to the network card,
这避免了操作系统与网卡交互，
and then they use network cards that have a special feature called RDMA,
然后他们使用具有 RDMA 特殊功能的网卡，
that allows the card to read and write memory from remote server
这允许网卡从远程服务器读取内存，
without actually having to interrupt you know that remote server,
而不必中断远程服务器，
and so this gives us
所以，这为我们提供了
really low latency network access to remote server, or to remote memory,
对远程服务器或远程内存的低延迟网络访问，
this is partially where the name FaRM comes from,
这就是 FaRM 名称的来源,
you know the R stands for remote and M for memory and Fa for fast.
R 代表远程， M 代表内存， Fa 代表快速。
So, those are the, those are the technologies they use,
所以，这些就是他们使用的技术，
and then you know to be able to really exploit these technologies
然后，为了能够真正利用这些技术，
drives them to a design,
驱动他们设计，
that uses optimistic concurrency control
使用乐观并发控制，
or OCC, the short version of this, so optimistic,
或 OCC ，这个的缩写，乐观的，
and in contrast with many of the designs that we've seen so far,
与我们到目前为止看到的许多设计相比，
where they use what was typically called pessimistic concurrency control scheme,
它们使用通常被称为悲观并发控制方案，
and pessimistic control scheme basically acquire locks
悲观控制方案获得锁
on you know the objects are being touched by the transaction,
在事务接触到对象时，
and so when they get to commit time,
所以当它们到达提交时间时，
they own all the locks for all the relevant objects
它们拥有所有相关对象的所有锁，
and just go ahead and commit,
继续并提交，
while with optimistic concurrency control,
而使用乐观并发控制，
you don't actually acquire locks,
你不需要获取锁，
particularly in FaRM,
特别是在 FaRM 中，
you don't require locks on the read transaction,
你不需要在读事务中获取锁，
and when you do go commit,
当你执行提交的时候，
you actually have to validate,
你必须验证，
that you read, you know read the most recent objects
你读取最近的对象，
and if so, you can go commit,
如果是这样，你可以提交，
and if you're not, you know you have to abort
如果不是，你必须中止，
and maybe try again.
也许还会再试一次。
And the reason they use optimization concurrence control,
他们使用乐观并发控制的原因，
as we'll see in a second,
我们稍后将会看到，
is really driven by the fact that they want to use RDMA.
是由他们想要使用 RDMA 这一事实驱动的。
Okay, so then the final component to this is certain overview,
好的，那么最后一个部分是概述，
this is really a research prototype,
这是一个研究原型，
so unlike Spanner, you know which is a deployed system,
与 Spanner 不同，是已部署的系统，
you know it's been active use,
它一直在活跃地使用，
FaRM is really a product of the research [] of Microsoft,
FARM 是微软研究的产品，
Microsoft research trying to explore new ideas,
微软研究试图探索新想法，
to see how, to see what can achieve higher
看看什么能获得更高的
or really high performance transaction systems,
或很高的性能的事务系统，
and this is just a very active research,
这是一项非常活跃的研究，
people would just love to have the power of transactions,
人们喜欢拥有事务的力量，
and but also the performance.
但是也想要性能。
Okay, so that's sort of short introduction,
好的，这是一个简短的介绍，
any questions so far?
到目前为止，有什么问题吗？
Okay, let's talk a little bit about the setup for FaRM.
好的，让我们来谈谈 FaRM 的设置。
And so there's basically 90 machines, 90 of these guys,
所以这里有 90 台机器，
they're connected by high-speed data center network,
它们通过高速数据中心网络连接，
and see a particular one,
看其中一个，
I'm just going to draw that as a single line,
我把它画成一条线，
of course, it's a switch network internally,
当然，内部是一个交换网络，
and basically shard,
然后分片，
the data is sharded across these different machines,
数据分片在这些不同的机器上，
and the level of sharding happens, some else called region,
根据分片的级别，一些也称为区域，
so region is 2 gigabyte,
所以区域是 2G 字节，
and you know those regions are sharded
这些区域分片在
across different networks and the different machines,
不同的网络，不同的机器上，
the region live in memory,
区域在内存中，
so this is just DRAM,
所以这是 DRAM ，
and not in for example on the disk,
而不是在磁盘上，
so basically, the total dataset of your database
所以，你的数据库的全部数据集
actually has to fit in the joint DRAMs of the machine that you're using,
必须与你使用的机器的联合 DRAM 相适应，
so if your dataset is larger than your current set of machines,
如果你的数据集大于你当前的计算机集，
you have to buy more machines, that get more DRAM,
你必须购买更多机器，拥有更多 DRAM ，
so they can actually fit.
这样它们才能适合。
And again, the reason why you know they want to use DRAM is,
他们想使用 DRAM 的原因是，
because they want [] bottleneck by the performance of storage devices,
他们想要[]存储设备性能方面的瓶颈，
and of course you know machine can fail,
当然，机器可能出现故障，
and if a machine fails, it uses loses DRAM,
如果机器出现故障，它会丢失 DRAM ，
and so therefore they use replication,
所以，他们使用复制，
and so they replicate regions across multiple machines,
他们在多台机器上复制区域，
one machine is primary for a region,
一台机器是一个区域的 primary ，
and that makes machine region might be replicated on another machine,
使区域可能被复制到另一台机器上，
which is in the backup,
在备机上，
so use primary backup for replication,
所以使用主备进行复制，
and so this region 1, you know region 2,
所以这是区域 1 ，区域 2 ，
you know the backup might be on the same machine as the primary
（2的）备份可能在（1的）主机的同一台机器上，
for backup for region 2,
作为区域 2 的备份，
and here we have the primary region 2.
这里我们有区域 2 的主机。
So this deals you know,
所以这决定了，
so one machine has a kernel panic
一台机器出现内核 panic ，
or some device goes that
或者某个设备死机，
or you know just crashes for some other reason,
或者只是因为其他原因而崩溃，
then there's a second machine,
然后还有第二台机器，
that actually has a copy of the data and just proceed from there.
它有数据的复制，并从那里继续进行。
Of course, then we need some way of keeping track of
当然，我们需要某种方法来跟踪
the mapping from regions to primaries and backups,
区域到主机和备机的映射，
and so they use a configuration manager,
所以，他们使用配置管理器，
a CM that sits on the side,
一个 CM 在这里，
and CM itself actually is coupled with a system that we've seen before zookeeper,
CM 本身与我们之前看过的 zookeeper 相结合，
and really the zookeeper and the configuration management that keep track of
zookeeper 和配置管理器跟踪，
the mapping you know from region number to the primary and whatever the backups,
从区域编号到主机和备机的映射，
for every region.
对于每个区域。
Okay?
好的?
Now there's one a serious problem of course here,
当然，现在这里有一个严重的问题，
I I talked about,
我讨论过，
like while primary with primary backup replication way,
使用主备方案，
so we have fault,
我们会有故障，
then you know one machine can fail,
一台机器可能会出故障，
now the machine can take over,
现在机器可以接手，
except the one sort of tricky case,
除了一种棘手的情况，
that this scheme can't handle so far,
到目前为止这个方案不能处理，
is when there's a correlated failure,
当出现相关的故障时，
for example there's a power failure of the data center,
例如，数据中心停电，
and all machines should now go down,
所有的机器都会停机，
and to handle that case,
为了处理这种情况，
basically the DRAM has it sits on a UPS,
DRAM 位于 UPS 上，
where every machine sits on an uninterruptible power supply,
每台机器都有一个不间断的电源，
so I'm going to draw these a big battery that sits on the side,
所以我要画一个大电池放在边上，
and the battery basically or UPS you know provides enough energy,
电池或者 UPS 提供足够的能量，
that if there's a global power failure,
如果发生全局停电，
the machine keep running for a little time,
机器会继续运转一小段时间，
and ended up a little time,
这一小段时间，
the machine can actually store,
机器可以存储，
the FaRM would like to store the data on on SSDs
FaRM 将数据存储在 SSD 上，
or basically just flush the contents of its memory,
或者只是刷新它的内存中的内容，
all the regions, all the transaction state, all logs for the transactions,
所有区域，所有事务状态，所有事务日志，
actually flushes it to SSD,
将它们刷新到 SSD 上，
so if there's a complete power failure of the whole data center,
所以，如果整个数据中心完全停电，
the data center at some point will come back up,
数据中心将在某个时间恢复运行，
and they can load you know the memory contents of the machines from the SSD,
它们可以从 SSD 中加载机器的内存内容，
and you know start basically running again,
重新开始运行，
and so this is basically the only place where the SSDs are being used,
这是唯一使用 SSD 的地方，
to deal with correlated failure many machines in the data center.
为了处理数据中心内的多台机器的相关故障。
Any questions so far?
到目前为止，有什么问题吗？
Okay, let me say a little bit about the software,
好的，让我简单介绍一下软件，
so in the regions,
所以在区域里，
so we have a region here,
我们在这里有一个区域，
in the region objects live,
在区域中有一些对象，
so you can just think about an array, region as an array of bytes,
所以你可以把区域想象成一个字节数组，
you know 2 gigabytes,
2G 字节，
and in you know array of bytes, objects live,
在字节对象数组中，有一些对象，
and objects have a unique identifier oid,
对象有唯一的标识符 oid ，
and the oid of an object is nothing else,
对象 oid 不是别的，
it's region number, [] the region number and then the address you know within that region,
它是[]区域编号和区域内的地址，
associated with every object,
与每个对象绑定，
there's a little bit of metadata for that particular object,
这里有一些对象的元数据，
and in particular for object header contains a 64 bit number,
对象头部包含一个 64 位数字，
and the number consists is basically a version number in the bottom 63
该数字包含底部 63 位版本号，
and then a lock bit, as we'll see in the top bit, in the high order bit,
然后是一个锁位，我们会在顶部看到，
so every object has this you know 64 bit number,
所以每个对象都有这个 64 位数字，
refer to as a version number,
称为版本号，
and then we'll see plays an important role in the optimistic concurrency control.
然后我们将看到它在乐观并发控制中起重要作用。
The way applications use you know this system,
应用程序使用这个系统的方式，
let me say a little bit about that,
让我稍微说一下，
so what's the application programmer interface.
应用程序编程接口是什么。
So the API is
所以 API 是，
you know you start transaction,
你启动事务，
and you read some objects,
读取一些对象，
so there is read call,
这是 read 调用，
and read call takes oid as an argument,
read 调用将 oid 作为参数，
the application then can manipulate,
然后，应用程序可以操作，
you know change the fields in the, in the object,
修改对象中的字段，
whatever add 1 to it,
不管什么，比如加 1 ，
and then at some point write the object,
然后在某个时刻写入对象，
write update the object itself using the write call
使用 write 调用更新对象自己，
and then you know commit it using txcommit.
然后使用 txcommit 提交它。
And it might also be the case that,
也可能是这种情况，
the transaction needs to abort,
事务需要中止，
because of the optimistic concurrency control,
因为是乐观并发控制，
in that case, the application will typically just retry the transaction,
在这种情况下，应用程序将重试事务，
and so in the transaction, the way it shows transaction here,
所以，在这里显示的事务中，
there's only one object manipulated,
只有一个对象操作，
yeah, but it seems actually manipulate many, many objects,
但它实际操作很多对象，
those objects could be on a different regions,
这些对象可能位于不同的区域，
and and so you know they have to have some plans,
所以它们必须有一些方案，
we'll see,
我们将会看到，
we're running some two-phase commit like protocol to do atomic operations
我们使用类似两阶段提交的协议来执行原子操作，
across objects living in different regions.
跨不同地区的对象。
Any sort of questions about the API and setup?
关于 API 和设置，有什么问题吗？
Sorry, the address oid, it is the address in the machine itself?
抱歉，地址 oid ，是在机器本身的地址吗？
Yeah, which is the offset within that region.
是的，是那个区域内的偏移量。
Okay?
好的？
The region could move, correct,
区域可以移动，
you know that the replicated or the configuration manager [] the mapping,
复制或配置管理器[]映射，
the actual address where the object might change,
对象可能更改的地址，
so this is a region number plus an offset,
所以这是一个区域编号加上一个偏移量，
a little bit there here, I should set offset.
在这里，我应该设置偏移量。
Sorry, I have another question that,
抱歉，我也有一个问题，
what was the design choice or design thinking behind making a global address space?
创建全局地址空间背后的设计选择或设计思想是什么？
The to have everything in the DRAM,
把所有东西都放在内存中，
not sure that answers your question, but,
我不确定这是否回答了你的问题，但是，
the whole goal of them is to actually run the transactions on an in-memory database,
它们的全部目标是在内存数据库上运行事务，
you know this whole trend of set of databases,
这是数据库的整体趋势，
where all the data is always in memory, is called in-memory databases,
所有数据始终在内存中，称为内存数据库，
driven by the fact that DRAM is [reasonably] cheap,
因为 DRAM 很便宜，
and so that would allow you to basically run transactions
这将允许你运行事务，
without actually having to go to persistent storage,
不需要访问持久化存储，
and they're basically jumping on that [] in-memory databases.
他们跳上了内存数据库。
I see, and that requires like a global address space they all share.
我明白了，这需要它们共享一个全局地址空间。
The address space is per machine, right,
地址空间是按机器的，
every machine has its own address space from 0 to whatever,
每台机器都有自己的地址空间，从 0 到任何东西，
and the the the the objects are really the global numbers or global names.
这些对象是全球编号或全局名称。
Thank you.
谢谢。
Okay, good.
好的，很好。
So let's talk so far,
那么我们谈到目前为止，
I think we basically sort of established
我认为我们已经建立了
you know they've gotten the stable storage devices out of the way,
他们已经排除了稳定的存储设备，
and so there's no bottleneck for reading writing storage devices,
所以，读写存储设备不存在瓶颈，
because they're basically not using them,
因为他们没有使用它们，
other than this is one exceptional case when the power fails.
一个例外的情况是电源故障。
And so the next set of things they focus on is
他们关注的下一组事情是是，
trying to reduce CPU utilization
试图降低 CPU 使用率
or try to be very efficient with the CPU
或者试图高效地使用 CPU
and be very efficient at the network.
并且在网络方面非常高效。
And there's two key ideas here,
这里有两个关键的想法，
that are pretty well known.
是众所周知的。
So the first one is kernel bypass,
第一个是内核旁路，
and the story that is reasonable simple,
这个故事很简单，
so we have FaRM that runs as a user level process,
我们 FaRM 作为用户进程运行，
on top of Windows, the Windows operating system,
在 Windows 操作系统上面，
so here's the operating system,
这是操作系统，
let's move a little bit on the side,
让我们往边上移一点，
and the operating system of course
操作系统当然，
and there are all the features for scheduling processes you know virtual memory,
有所有的功能，进程调度，虚拟内存，
standard operating system,
标准的操作系统，
and it also have drivers for hardware devices,
它也有硬件设备的驱动程序，
and like one of the hardware devices is a network interface card,
并且其中一个硬件设备是网卡，
and you know typically you know the OS driver inside of it,
通常操作系统驱动程序在里面，
that programs the network interface card,
对那个网卡编程，
so read and write registers on the network interface card to basically send a packet
所以读写网卡上的寄存器发送包，
or to reconfigure the network interface card, etc, etc.
或者重新配置网卡，等等。
So the typical way you know that you know applications interact with network card is,
应用程序与网卡交互的通常方式是，
they make system calls to the kernel,
它们对内核进行系统调用，
and ask the kernel to basically send a packet,
要求内核发送一个包，
and that you know involves the operating system,
这涉及操作系统，
involves TCP stack, the network stack,
涉及到 TCP 栈，网络栈，
and it tends to be quite expensive,
它往往相当昂贵，
and so they want to avoid this this overhead,
所以他们想要避免这个开销，
you know going entering the kernel running TCP, etc,
进入内核，运行 TCP 等，
and the way they do that is something that is technique called kernel bypass,
他们这样做的方式是一种被称为内核旁路的技术，
and network card is sort of collaboration between the network card and the operating system,
网卡是网卡和操作系统之间的协作，
and basically what it does is,
它所做的是，
that the queues that the network interface has,
它对网卡的队列排序，
here're some queues, for example send queue and receive queue,
这是一些队列，比如发送队列和接收队列，
those queues are basically directly mapped or into the address space of the application,
这些队列直接映射或进入应用程序的地址空间，
so the application can ask you know operating system,
所以，应用程序可以请求操作系统，
please you know take some queues that the NIC has
请取出网卡所有的一些队列，
and map them into the address space of the application,
并将它们映射到应用程序的地址空间中，
so you can just think about this sort of queue
所以，你可以考虑这些队列，
basically is directly accessible from the user level application,
可以从用户级应用程序直接访问，
so the user level application, you know can basically now
所以用户应用程序现在可以，
read and write you know commands or packets into the network interface card,
读写命令或包到网卡，
without actually having to involve the operating system at all.
而不需要涉及到操作系统。
So this cuts the whole operating system out of the picture
所以这把整个操作系统都排除在外了，
and improves you know performance considerably.
大大提高了性能。
In the case of FaRM,
在 FaRM 的情况下，
they also don't want to use interrupts,
他们也不想使用中断，
so one way of delivering a packet, correct is
一种传递包的方式是，
the packet comes in,
当包进入的时候，
the network interface card delivers an interrupt to the operating system,
网卡向操作系统发送中断，
the operating system then alerts the application that the packet has arrived,
然后操作系统告诉应用包已经到达，
and [] trying to avoid that cost,
试图避免这一成本，
and the way they avoid that cost is
避免这一成本的方法是
basically they poll the receive queue.
他们轮询接收队列。
So there's basically an user level thread,
所以有一个用户级别的线程，
you know that sits in the FaRM application,
它位于 FaRM 应用程序中，
and basically does nothing else than sort of reading the receive queue,
除了读取接收队列之外，什么也不做，
to see if actually packet is available.
查看包是否可用。
And so that requires you know you need a [],
所以这需要一个[]，
so that avoids the use of interrupts,
这就避免了中断的使用，
and you know and the cost of basically having a polling thread,
有一个轮询线程的代价，
that's you know sits there doing nothing else than polling,
在那里，除了轮询什么也不做，
and FaRM turns out this thread actually switches back and forth
FaRM 这个线程来回切换，
between running some application code and polling the NIC.
在运行应用程序代码和轮询网卡之间。
So that's sort of kernel bypass,
所以这是内核旁路，
and this is a reasonable standard,
这是一个[合理的标准]，
some people may, some of you maybe know familiar with DPDK,
你们中的一些人可能熟悉 DPDK ，
which is data plane development kit,
它是数据平面开发工具包，
which a development kit to basically leverage you know kernel bypass.
是一个可以利用内核旁路的开发工具包。
It's a reasonable standard thing,
这是一个合理的标准，
is available on many operating systems.
在许多操作系统上都可以使用。
So then the next you know sort of piece of technology they use,
下一个他们使用的技术，
is a little bit but also well known as wide and standardized,
有一点，但也是众所周知，广泛和标准化的，
many network cards supported
许多网卡支持，
or more high-end network card supported,
或者更高端的网卡支持，
and that's something was called RDMA,
这就是所谓的 RDMA ，
which stands for remote, remote direct memory access.
它表示远程直接内存访问。
The basic idea is that,
基本的想法是，
you know this requires NICs that actually understand RDMA,
这需要网卡理解 RDMA ，
and so here we have cable,
这里有电缆，
here we have NIC on the other side,
另一边有网卡，
the operating system may be sitting on top of it,
操作系统可能在它的上面，
you know where we have FaRM,
这里我们有 FaRM ，
and basically you know the application on the side, on the center side,
应用程序在旁边，
you know can basically put particular packet into the send queue,
可以把特定的包放入发送队列，
and you know send RDMA packet,
发送 RDMA 包，
and so basically somewhere is a bit the header of the packet,
在数据包的头部有一位，
saying, like hey I'm an RDMA packet,
表示，我是个 RDMA 包，
and then the NIC will send it over to the NIC, the destination NIC,
然后网卡会将其发送到目标网卡，
the destination NIC sees that this is a special packet, an RDMA packet,
目标网卡看出这是一个特殊的包，一个 RDMA 包，
and looks at the instruction that goes along with the RDMA packet,
并查看与 RDMA 包一起的指令，
so the instruction might be
这个指令可能是，
read a particular memory location or write a particular memory location,
读取特定内存位置或写入特定内存位置，
so here so for example,
举个例子，
let's say it's a read operation,
假设这是一个读操作，
and the read operation will be safely takes an address,
读取操作将安全地获取地址，
and it allows the NIC
并且它允许网卡，
to basically read the address straight out of memory, out of RAM,
直接从内存中读取地址，
so for example let's say you know here we have our region,
假设这里有我们的区域，
you know with objects in it,
里面有对象，
and the sending FaRM application can just say,
发送 FaRM 应用程序可以说，
okay, I wanna read you know this particular address,
好的，我想读取这个特定地址，
you know which corresponds to address with this object o,
对应于这个对象 o 的地址，
and will send an RDMA packet to the NIC on the other side,
将向另一端的网卡发送 RDMA 数据包，
the NIC is that there is an RDMA packet,
网卡是有一个 RDMA 数据包，
and basically read you know from memory,
从内存中读取，
the value stored at that particular location,
存储在特定位置的值，
and sends them straight back you know to the source.
然后直接把它们送回源头。
And what is cool about this technology is that,
这项技术的酷的地方在于，
the NIC can do this
网卡可以做这个，
without actually interrupting or interfering with the server at all,
根本不需要中断或干扰服务器，
it doesn't have to generate an interrupt,
它不需要产生中断，
doesn't have to run any code on the the processors,
不需要在处理器上运行任何代码，
that run the operating system, the application,
运行操作系统，应用程序，
instead you know NICs has firmware that runs executes those instructions,
相反，网卡具有固件执行这些命令，
and loads you know the value stored those memory,
加载存储在这些内存中的值，
request memory addresses straight into a response packet
请求内存地址直接进入响应包，
and sends response packet back,
并发回数据包，
and then of course on the receiving side,
当然，在接收端，
you know that will show up in the receive queue,
这将显示在接收队列中，
and so far, you know at some point,
到目前为止，在某个点上，
you know hold the receive queue and see actually the result of that RDMA.
持有接收队列，并看到 RDMA 的结果。
This, this particular version that I am describing here,
我在这里描述的这个版本，
the paper refers to as one-sided RDMA,
论文将其称为单边 RDMA ，
and that's typically refers to the paper to read operations.
这通常指的是读取操作。
Professor.
教授。
Yeah, go ahead.
好的，继续。
Sorry professor,
抱歉，教授，
can can you repeat,
你能重复一下，
how how the polling of the like NIC queues works on the on the client
客户端的网卡队列是如何工作的，
or yeah like.
或者，是的。
There's almost nothing to it,
这几乎没有什么，
the the client just has a thread that reads a particular memory location,
客户端只有一个读取特定内存位置的线程，
and which indicates whether a packet has arrived or not,
表示数据包是否已经到达，
and when the NIC receives packets, sticks in the receive queue,
当网卡接收到包，放入接收队列中，
and as a side of setting in the receive queue,
作为接收队列中设置的一侧，
you know the flag bit you know turns into 1,
标志位变为 1 ，
and the application knows, oh yeah there's a packet there.
应用程序知道那里有一个包。
Is it a specific thread that you know that polls or like?
是不是一个特殊的线程轮询？
Yeah, they're in their system, they have specific threads,
是的，他们的系统里，有特定的线程，
that actually are dedicated to polling the queues.
专门用于轮询队列。
Okay, thanks.
好的，谢谢。
Sorry, I'm also confused here,
抱歉，这里我也比较疑惑，
so does the NIC cooperate with this system or regularly doing a job,
那么，网卡是否与系统合作，正常工作，
like as in any regular NIC.
就像普通的网卡一样。
Okay, this is not you know whatever your standard NIC, right,
好的，这不是普通网卡，
this NIC that supports both kernel bypass and remote direct memory access RDMA,
这个网卡同时支持内核旁路和远程直接内存访问 RDMA ，
in the, typically for NIC to support kernel bypass,
通常，网卡为了支持内核旁路，
it means it has to have multiple receive and send queues,
这意味着它必须有多个接收和发送队列，
and it just gives a pair of send or receive queues to an application,
它只向应用程序提供一对发送或接收队列，
and it cannot like,
它不能，
of course,
当然，
you can't have a send receive queue for every process running on your machine,
你不能让计算机上运行的每个进程都有一个发送接收队列，
so typically they're like 16 of them, or 32 of them,
所以它们通常是 16 个或者 32 个，
and you know get some of them to particular OS,
把其中的一些放到特定的操作系统上，
basically allow some applications to own basically send and receive queue.
允许一些应用程序拥有发送接收队列。
Thanks so much.
非常感谢。
It also means there's a specific support for RDMA and make it all work out,
这也意味着有对 RDMA 的支持，并使它正常工作，
you know, so it requires a NIC that is a reasonable sophisticated,
所以它需要一个相当复杂的网卡，
although it's a reasonable standard, these days.
尽管如今这是一个合理的标准。
Okay, so that's one side of RDMA,
好的，这是 RDMA 的一个方面，
they also use RDMA to do writes,
它们还使用 RDMA 进行写入，
and to actually implement RPC,
真正实现 RPC ，
and so, there's, they typically call this write RDMA in the paper,
他们在论文中把这个称为 写 RDMA ，
is basically the same thing,
基本上是相同的事情，
except the sender could put in the RDMA packet,
除了发送方可以放入 RDMA 包，
saying like oh this is a write operation,
说这是一个写操作，
and write you know the following bytes to a particular address,
将以下字节写入特定地址，
and the paper uses two places or two things,
这篇论文使用了两个地方或两个东西，
where writes are actually going to,
这些地方用到了写入，
[] written directly with RDMA,
直接用 RDMA 写入，
but there's two other data structures that are being written with write RDMAs,
但还有另外两个数据结构使用 写RDMA 写入，
one is a log,
一个是日志，
you'll see the [rule] the log later,
稍后你会看到日志的规则，
and this is a really [] transactions,
这是一个事务，
so it has committed record, logging records, etc etc,
所以它有提交记录，日志记录，等等，
and so if the source you know once append a log record to this particular log,
所以，如果源头将日志记录附加到这个日志，
I can just do write RDMA,
我可以执行 写RDMA ，
and and then the receiving NIC will
然后，接收网卡会
add you know the new entry in the log to the specified location.
将日志中的新条目添加到指定位置。
Okay?
好的?
And so that means like the sender,
所以这意味着就像发送者，
and there's one of these queues and one of these logs per sender receiver pair,
每个发送方和接收方对都有一个队列和一个日志，
so that sender actually can manage and know
所以发送者可以管理和知道
what the beginning and the end of the log are.
日志开头和结尾是什么。
Then, in addition to that,
然后，除此之外，
there's something there message queues and also one per pair,
有一些消息队列也是每对一个，
and these are basically used to implement RPCs,
这些用于实现 RPC ，
so if you want to do remote procedure call,
所以，如果你想要进行远程过程调用，
the client, the sender makes write RDMA RDMA packet,
客户端，发送方制作 写RDMA 包，
writes you know the data, the message basically into the remote message queue,
将数据，消息写入远程消息队列，
there's a thread sitting on the destination side,
在目标一侧也有一个线程，
that is basically polling that message queue or polling all the message queues,
轮询消息队列或轮询所有消息队列，
if it sees a message, you know it processes the message,
如果它看到一条消息，它会处理消息，
and can then send a response back, using a write RDMA,
然后可以使用 写RDMA 发回响应，
and this turns out to be cheaper implementing remote procedure call using RDMA,
使用 RDMA 实现远程过程调用更[便宜]，
it turns out to be cheaper than basically using sort of standard RPC packet,
它比使用某种标准 RPC 包更[便宜]，
that you know since packet using a regular NIC, but without RDMA
数据包使用普通网卡，但没有 RDMA ，
and has a thread on the other side you know that response.
在另一边有一个线程响应。
Okay?
好的?
Is there any validation step here,
这里是否有任何验证步骤，
to make sure that you're you're only writing to a region of memory,
为了确保你只写入内存区域，
that's expressly allowed for RDMA,
这是明确允许 RDMA 的，
you know don't write application to application memory or something.
不要写到应用程序内存或其他什么地方。
Yeah, so there are all kinds of,
是的，有各种各样的，
you know this is sort of the high-level idea,
这是一种高层次的想法，
talk into details here,
在这里讨论详细信息，
so when you sort of set up one of these RDMA,
所以，当你设置这些 RDMA 时，
in order to do this one-sided RDMA or write RDMAs,
为了做这种单边 RDMA 或写入 RDMA ，
you first have to do connection setup,
你首先必须进行连接设置，
there's a negotiation step between the sender and the receiver to setup,
在发送者和接收者之间有一个协商步骤来设置，
basically like it's almost like a TCP channel,
它就像一个 TCP 通道，
except you know RDMA doesn't use TCP,
除了 RDMA 不使用 TCP ，
but it sets up a connection oriented reliable, ordered channel,
但是它建立了面向连接的可靠、有序的通道，
and so the security checks and access control checks
所以，安全检查和访问控制检查
are happening at the point of the setup.
是在设置时进行的。
So would you have to do that between every pair of machines?
那么，你需要在每一对机器之间执行这个操作吗？
Yes.
是的。
So that would become really costly to add,
所以这将变得非常昂贵的添加，
like one machine to a large cluster, right?
比如一台机器对一个大集群，是吗？
You have n square RDMA connections,
你有 n 的平方个连接，
and otherwise we would have n square TCP connections,
否则我们将有 n 的平方个 TCP 连接，
not clear as a major difference there.
不清楚是不是有很大的区别。
And so just to clarify,
为了确认一下，
so the message in the logs,
日志中的信息，
basically they both sit also in memory,
它们也在内存中，
they just sit in different places than where the objects sit.
它们只是在与对象不同的地方。
Yeah, exactly,
是的，没错，
so if you do,
所以如果你这样做，
so this is sort of on here on the right,
那么这就是右边的这个，
is a picture of the memory layout of the FaRM process,
是 FaRM 进程的内存布局图片，
you know there's a region table or an object table,
有一个区域表或一个对象表，
and there are regions in the memory of the server,
在服务器的内存中有区域，
these regions have objects in them,
这些区域中有对象，
and in addition to the regions,
除了这些区域之外，
there are message queues and there are logs.
还有消息队列和日志。
I see,
我明白了，
and also for the NIC to support the direct access from memory,
而且为了让网卡支持从内存直接访问，
so since here we don't have any software involved,
由于我们在这里没有涉及任何软件，
since the NIC can directly access the memory
网卡可以直接访问内存，
without even notifying the application or the OS,
甚至不需要通知应用或操作系统，
shouldn't be some coordination on the hardware level,
不应该在硬件层面上进行一些协调，
or at least some support also from the processor to this feature.
或者至少从处理器支持这个特性。
Yeah, so there's, it's basically,
是的，所以，
you know the NIC can read or write read or write cache lines atomically
网卡可以原子地读写缓存行，
and so to support this,
为了支持这一点，
you know there's an interface you know to the memory system between NIC,
有一个接口在内存系统和网卡之间，
and this has to be carefully setup you know between OS
必须在操作系统仔细设置，
and when the connection setup is done.
当连接设置完成时。
I see, thank you.
我明白了，谢谢。
Sorry, the write to RDMA on the right side that is red,
抱歉，右侧的 写入RDMA 是红色的，
what happens there?
那里发生了什么？
So, the sender, the left machine can do write RDMA,
所以，发送者，左边的机器可以执行 写入RDMA ，
which basically sends an write RDMA packets
发送 写入RDMA 包到右侧，
to the right side you know the destination,
到右边的目标，
and the NIC you know sees this is a write RDMA packet,
网卡会看到这是一个 写入RDMA 包，
and will write the content that came in over the network
并将写入网络来的内容，
to the address that's specified in the write RDMA command.
写入 RDMA 命令中指定的地址。
But that would be just.
但这将是。
And so there's a remote machine,
所以有一台远程机器，
can just write the memory location set of addresses on the destination machine,
可以写入内存地址在目标机器上，
without actually having the server you know being involved,
在没有服务器参与的情况下，
other than doing setup, of course.
当然，除了设置之外。
Thank you.
谢谢。
So, quick question,
所以，我有个小问题，
so that the, the queue, the queue and the NIC is only used for read RDMA,
所以队列和网卡只用于读 RDMA ，
like the write, write directly to memory at the receiver.
（因为）写入直接到接收者的内存。
Yeah, on the on the,
是的，在，
okay, so there on the write RDMA,
好的，在写入 RDMA 中，
as you maybe noticed in the paper,
你可能在报纸上注意到的，
there can be an acknowledgment coming back,
可能会有确认，
so, if the sender sends does write RDMA,
所以，如果发送方发送写入 RDMA ，
it can wait from an acknowledgement, from the receiving NIC,
它可以等待来自接收网卡的确认，
that actually indeed performed the write RDMA.
表示执行了写入 RDMA 。
Okay, thanks.
好的，谢谢。
And that will play an important role.
这将发挥重要作用。
Any more questions about this part?
关于这一部分，还有什么问题吗？
This sort of a cool piece of technology,
这是一种很酷的技术，
you know that's come into existence pretty widespread in the last decade,
在过去的十年里，这种情况相当普遍地出现，
and basically they want to leverage it,
他们想要利用这一点，
because it allows them to get very, get something the latency
因为这让他们获得延迟，
to actually do one of these one-sided RDMAs about 5 microseconds,
进行单边 RDMA 约为 5 微秒，
so very low latency,
所以非常低的延迟，
much much much faster, correct,
非常快，
for example reading or writing a disk,
例如，读取或写入磁盘，
and not much slower, slower than writing your own memory,
比写入你自己的内存慢不了多少，
but you know pretty fast,
非常快，
because it allows you to do is one microsecond, a million packets per second,
因为它允许你做一微秒，每秒一百万个包，
pretty impressive.
令人印象深刻。
Okay?
好的?
So this so far basically standard technology, right,
到目前为止，这是标准技术，
you know cutting edge, but you know standard.
前沿的，但是标准的。
So, the real challenge that the paper address is,
所以，这篇论文解决的真正挑战是，
it's actually how to use RDMA,
是如何使用 RDMA ，
both write RDMA and one-sided RDMA actually doing transactions,
写入 RDMA 和单边 RDMA 进行事务，
so the challenge this paper address is transactions using RDMA.
所以，论文所解决的挑战是事务使用 RDMA 。
And you know sort of see that this is challenge,
你可以看到这是一个挑战，
we have to think a little bit about,
我们必须考虑一下，
all the protocols that we've seen so far,
到目前为止我们看到的所有协议，
so it sort of protocols for you know for transactions, two-phase commit, etc,
事务的协议，两阶段提交等，
all those protocols have required server-side participation,
所有这些协议都需要服务器端参与，
and for example, what I mean with that is
例如，我的意思是，
you know the client sends a request for the transaction coordinator,
客户端发送请求到事务协调者，
sends a request to one of the participants,
发送请求到其中一个参与者，
for example to require a lock on a particular object,
比如获取某个对象的锁，
and you know just wait you know on the server or the receiver
等待服务器或接收者，
until the lock actually it becomes available,
直到锁变得可用，
or you know runs you know the server runs some validation step,
或者服务器运行一些验证步骤，
you know to see if the the transaction can be committed or not,
查看事务是否能被提交，
and so in all those cases basically,
所以在所有这些情况中，
if you have some server-side participation,
如果你有一些服务器端参与，
that means that you have to run code on the server,
意味着你必须在服务器上运行代码，
and you know that is sort of counter to what RDMA gives you, right,
这与 RDMA 给你带来的是相反的，
RDMA actually doesn't provide you the ability to run code on the server,
RDMA 没有为你提供在服务器上运行代码的能力，
and so the the designers or the authors of this paper
所以，这篇论文的设计者或作者
have to come up with sort of protocols,
必须想出一种协议，
that allow you to implement two-phase commit and transactions in general
允许你实现两阶段提交和事务
to without actually or trying to reduce your server-side participation,
不使用或试着减少服务器端参与，
so that they can reuse some part of the operations using RDMA,
他们可以重用 RDMA 进行某些操作，
and you know some using remote procedure calls,
有些使用远程过程调用，
as usual sort of traditional would do,
像传统做法一样，
in traditional designs, that we've seen in the last couple weeks.
在过去的几周里我们看到的传统设计。
And so that's sort of the central challenge in in this paper,
这就是这篇论文的核心挑战，
and this pushes them in this direction to solve that problem,
这促使他们朝着这个方向去解决这个问题，
the high-level strategy that they use is,
他们使用的高级策略是，
the high level strategy uses is optimistic concurrency control.
使用的高级策略是乐观并发控制。
And and you know really did really where the shine for them is on read operations,
他们真正的闪光点是在读取操作上，
because basically the basic plan is read objects,
因为基本计划是读取对象，
that are part of the transaction without requiring locks,
这些是不需要锁的事务部分，
for example require locks you know that would mean interrupting maybe the server,
例如，需要锁，这意味着可能会中断服务器，
the server has to do some work,
服务器必须做一些工作，
and then maybe block the client
可能会阻止客户端，
until the lock is available and then return the object,
直到锁可用，然后返回对象，
and you know that is not really suitable or nice nicely with or lines up nicely with RDMA,
这与 RDMA 并不是很合适，
and so they're going to go to optimistic scheme,
所以，他们将采取乐观的方案，
where basically reading objects is not going to require locks at all,
其中读取对象不需要任何锁，
you can fetch an object and start using it,
你获取一个对象并开始使用它，
and as we'll see,
正如我们将看到的，
you know of course you need to have some mechanism
当然你需要一些机制
to discover whether you're reading an old version or new version,
来发现读取的是旧版本还是新版本，
and this is where the version numbers are going to play an important role.
这就是版本号将发挥重要作用的地方。
So when you read an object in FaRM,
所以当你读取 FaRM 中的一个对象，
you get the object back,
你把对象拿回来，
and you get also the version number back to that object,
你也把那个对象的版本号拿回来，
and then basic idea is that,
然后基本的想法是，
at the point of commit,
在提交的时候，
we're going to do a validation step,
我们要做一个验证步骤，
to check that the objects being write at the beginning of the transaction,
检查事务开始时写入的对象，
actually having been modified.
已经被修改了。
And so during validation check step,
所以，在验证检查步骤期间，
we're basically going to check for conflict,
我们要检查冲突，
and the conflict is basically,
冲突是，
if the version number has been incremented,
如果版本号已递增，
you know since you know the coordinator actually read the object,
从协调者读取了对象，
so if the version number are different,
所以如果版本号是不同的，
different, then the transaction is aborted,
是不同的，则事务中止，
and if they're saying, are still the same,
如果仍然是一样的，
that basically means that nobody, no other transaction modified the transaction, the object,
这意味着没有其他事务修改了对象，
and then we can actually go ahead and commit.
然后我们可以继续并提交。
Of course, in the case of abort,
当然，在中止的情况下，
you know typical what happen is that,
通常会发生的情况是，
the the client you know maybe run the whole transaction again,
客户端可能会再次运行整个事务，
perhaps waiting for a little while before actually doing it,
也许在开始之前等一段时间，
for some random period of time.
一段随机的时间。
So that's the basic plan, right,
所以这就是基本的计划，
so this is optimistic scheme,
这是一个乐观的方案，
so that reads can completely exploit RDMA,
这样读取可以完全利用 RDMA ，
and as we'll see,
正如我们将看到的，
in fact, read won't require any state changes on the servers at all.
读取不需要服务器上的任何状态变化。
And so this is basically sort of the basic idea behind figure 4,
所以这是图 4 背后的基本思想，
except you know we'll see in a second,
除了，我们很快就会看到，
there's quite a bit more complications to it.
这件事要复杂得多。
So this again, sort of I think I used this phrase in a little while ago,
所以这也是，我想我用过了这个短语，
a couple lectures ago,
几节课前，
the optimistic schema in contrast to the pessimistic scheme is,
乐观方案与悲观方案相反的是，
you're basically going to assume that you're allowed to do the operation,
你假设你被允许执行操作，
and if it turns out you're not allowed, to sort of apologize and abort,
如果你不被允许，只需要道歉和中止，
in the pessimistic case,
在悲观的情况下，
you basically first ask for approval to do the operation by acquiring locks,
你首先通过获取锁来请求批准进行操作，
and then you know you basically guaranteed,
然后你被保证，
at commit time, you can actually commit.
在提交时，你可以提交。
Okay?
好的?
Any questions about optimistic concurrency control at this high level?
对于高级别的乐观并发控制，有什么问题吗？
Just a question about the version numbers,
只是一个关于版本号的问题，
how do they ensure that two different [],
他们如何确保两个不同的[]，
that there's like consistency across different objects,
两个不同的对象之间具有一致性，
so that you're now reading one object and then later reading another object,
你先读取一个对象，然后再读取另一个对象，
but those, but a transaction modified some of those in between.
但是一个事务修改了其中的一些。
Yeah, well, that's a great question,
是的，这是个很好的问题，
and so let's, I think we're going to get out,
所以，我想我们要离开了，
just gotta dive into actually figure 4,
只需要深入到图 4 ，
and which I think should be the core of this paper.
我认为这是论文的核心。
So let's look at figure 4,
让我们看一下图 4 ，
and, oops, not that one.
糟糕，不是那个。
Alright, here figure 4,
好的，这是图 4 ，
we're going to spend quite a bit of time basically talking about figure 4.
我们将花相当多的时间来讨论图 4 。
So the first you know things get oriented in this figure 4,
所以图 4 中的第一个东西，
you know we see,
我们看到，
so we have a transaction coordinator, the C here,
所以我们有一个事务协调者，这里的 C ，
and it's really the transaction coordinator is an application,
事务协调者是一个应用程序，
and the application runs on the same machine,
应用程序运行在相同的机器上，
is one of those 90 machines,
是 90 台机器中的一台，
but the way I'm going to think about it,
但我会这样考虑，
for the rest of those lectures,
对于剩余的课程，
that it runs on a separate machine,
它在一台单独的机器上运行，
I don't really care about it that much, okay?
我不太关心它，好吗？
And then, there are different shards,
然后，有不同的分片，
in this case there are 3 shards, 1 2 and 3,
在这种情况下，有 3 个分片， 1 2 和 3 ，
and each shard is replicated twice,
每个分片被复制两次，
one's in the primary, one's in the backup.
一个在主服务器，一个在备服务器。
Then you know we'll see that,
然后我们会看到，
this is the execution phase of the transaction,
这是事务的执行阶段，
so the transaction is two phases,
所以事务有两个阶段，
one is the execution phase, and then commit phase,
一个是执行阶段，然后是提交阶段，
and during the execution phase,
在执行阶段期间，
this is where the transaction is run,
这是事务运行的地方，
so does it begin, does read,
那么它执行开始，执行读取，
for example, in this case, the 3 objects are being read,
例如，在这种情况中， 3 个对象被读取，
and one that was located, whose primary in,
一个位于，它的主服务器，
one object that actually sit in shard 1,
一个对象在分片 1 ，
one object that's sit in shard 3,
一个对象在分片 3 ，
one objects sit in shard 2, alright, region.
一个对象在分片 2 ，区域 2 。
And the we can see,
我们可以看到，
actually we look a little bit ahead,
我们向前看一点，
we'll see that the,
我们将会看到，
the two of these objects are actually being written,
两个对象正在被写入，
and one of them is being read,
一个正在被读取，
so the object from number shard 3,
所以，来自分片 3 的对象，
this is just a read operation,
这是一个读操作，
and these are write operations,
这些是写操作，
or these are read operations,
或者这些是读操作，
but those objects are going to be modified.
但这些对象将被修改。
So basically as the transaction runs,
所以，随着事务的运行，
you know it fetches objects from different machines, modifies them locally,
它从不同的机器获取对象，在本地修改它们，
and then in the commit phase, the changes are being applied,
然后在提交阶段，应用更改，
and of course you know the whole challenge here is that,
当然，这里的整个挑战是，
in the end we want to achieve strict serializability.
最终，我们希望实现严格的可串行化。
And in some ways, the protocol for,
在某些方面，协议，
at least writes always follows a very similar two-phase commit protocols,
至少写入的协议总是遵循非常类似的两阶段提交协议，
that we've seen in the past,
这是我们过去看到的，
there are differences in the details,
在细节上有所不同，
but the basic strategy is the same,
但基本策略是相同的，
and you know we can sort of,
我们可以，
so let's assume that you know we're done with the execution phase,
我们假设我们已经完成了执行阶段，
so we're we're at the end of the transaction,
所以我们在事务的末尾，
and the transaction is going to try to commit,
事务将尝试提交，
that transaction that could be two outcomes,
事务可能会有两种结果，
you know actually you know successfully commits or actually aborts,
成功提交或中止，
and the aborts because some other transaction ran concurrently
中止是因为其他事务同时运行，
and modifies one of the objects,
并且修改了其中一个对象，
that we write or were trying to write.
我们写入或想要写入。
And so the first thing,
所以，第一件事，
that sort of protocol, the commit phase basically has 5 steps,
协议的提交阶段有 5 个步骤，
you know the locking step, the validation step,
加锁步骤，验证步骤，
the commit backup step, the commit primary
提交备份步骤，提交 primary 步骤，
and then the truncate,
然后是截断，
and the truncate basically runs almost lazily
截断运行得[很慢]，
and so it's not particularly important,
所以这并不是很重要，
basically for our perspective,
从我们的角度来看，
basically the point of interest where things are stopping is here,
有趣的事情停止的地方就是这里，
so that's sort of the end of the transaction is.
这就是事务的结束。
Okay, so each of these objects have said before,
好的，这些对象之前都说过，
you know when you read them has a version number,
当你读到它们，有一个版本号，
here's a version number,
这是一个版本号，
and there are modifies it locally,
在本地修改它们，
then at the point of this,
然后在这一点上，
you know when when this this is the commit point,
这是提交点，
where when the application calls end of transaction,
当应用调用结束事务时，
the protocol, but this whole commit phase protocol kicks in.
整个提交阶段协议才起作用。
And so the first thing it does is,
所以它做的第一件事是，
what's called the locking step, step number 1,
所谓的锁步骤，步骤 1 ，
and the goal here, in this step is
这一步的目标是，
to basically acquire locks on all the objects that are being written,
获取正在写入的所有对象的锁，
and so we can see you know based on this diagram,
所以我们可以看到，根据这张图，
that apparently two objects are being written,
显然有两个对象正在被写入，
namely the this object,
即这个对象，
because context is the primary of shard 1, region 1,
因为上下文是分片 1 ，区域 1 ，
and then this object is being read,
然后这个对象被读取，
that is actually located on region 2, right,
它位于区域 2 ，
apparently the third object, that we read you know for primary 3,
显然，我们读取第三个对象是 primary 3 的，
it's not being write,
它没有被写入，
because it doesn't participate in the locking phase.
因为它不参与锁阶段。
So in the locking phase,
所以在锁阶段，
the arrows actually have all kinds of different meanings.
箭头有各种不同的含义。
So these dashed arrows are one-sided RDMAs,
所以这些虚线箭头是单面 RDMA ，
so those objects are being read with RDMA,
这些对象是使用 RDMA 读取的，
they're just fetched from the remote memory location,
它们从远程内存位置获取，
and [] locally you know to the to the memory of the application or coordinator.
[]本地到应用程序或协调者的内存。
The solid ones are write RDMAs,
实线的是写入 RDMA ，
and and in this particular case,
在这个案例中，
they depend on lock entry to the, to the log of the primary,
它们依赖于主服务器的锁条目，
so the primary has a log,
所以主服务器有一个日志，
every primary has a log,
每个主服务器都有一个日志，
so I'm just gonna draw it like this,
所以我画成这样，
and actually use a different color,
使用不同的颜色，
so here we have the primary i with a log,
所以这里我们有 Pi 日志，
and basically the the the coordinator, it's a commit record,
协调者，这是一个提交记录，
no, sorry, sorry, lock record is called to the log,
不是，抱歉，锁记录到日志中，
I'm going to make it a big record,
我让它是一个大的记录，
I can write down what's in it,
我可以写下里面的东西，
and it is [] version number, the time of the read or write
它是版本号，读写时间，
and when the object is read,
当对象被读取时，
so that version number that came out here,
版本号从这里出来，
that goes back into the log record,
回到日志记录中的，
the object id that's being read and the new value for the object,
读取的对象 id 和对象的新值，
and so this record is just appended you know to the
所以，这条记录追加到
you know primary 1 and primary 2's log,
primary 1 和 primary 2 的日志，
using write RDMA.
使用写入 RDMA ，
And so there's some thread sitting on those machines,
所以这些机器上有一些线程，
that looks at these logs and then actually does some operations,
查看这些日志，然后执行一些操作，
so in this particular case,
所以在这个案例中，
if there's a thread sitting on P1 and P2,
有线程在 P1 P2 上，
you know monitors or spins or polls this log,
监控、旋转或轮询这个日志，
and sees there's a new log record,
看到有一个新的日志记录，
and then in this particular case, what it will do,
然后在这种情况下，它会做什么，
it will try to get a lock on the object,
它将尝试获取对象的锁，
you know that actually is listed in the in the transaction,
在事务中列出的，
somewhere, there's an object,
在某个地方，有一个对象，
and that object have some data in it
对象中包含一些数据，
and it has these lock bit and version number in it.
它里面有这些锁位和版本号。
And so P1 has one object,
所以 P1 有一个对象，
you know that is being modified by coordinator,
这是由协调者修改的，
P2 has another object, that is modified by the coordinator,
P2 有另一个对象，由协调者修改，
and basically the, the primary tries to be required the lock on the, on the object,
primary 尝试获取对象的锁，
using test-and-set instruction.
使用 test-and-set 指令，
And so it will try to set lock bit,
所以，它将尝试设置锁位，
and if the lock bit is 0,
如果锁位为 0 ，
and and the lock bit is 0
锁位是 0 ，
and successfully set the bit to 1,
并成功地将位设置为 1 ，
then it knows that, the primary knows that actually acquire the lock,
然后 primary 知道获取了锁，
and in that case and we'll send one RDMA message back,
在这种情况下，我们将发回一条 RDMA 消息，
to append a message to the coordinator's message queue,
将消息附加到协调者的消息队列，
saying okay, you successfully acquired locks for these particular objects.
说好的，你成功地获得了这些对象的锁。
If the transaction, if the lock was already taken by another transaction,
如果锁已经被另一个事务获取，
and then at that point in time,
然后在那个时间点，
the transaction is aborted,
事务被中止，
and so so when the primary i tries to get the lock,
所以当 primary i 试图获取锁的时候，
finds out that the lock is already set,
发现锁已经设置好了，
using test-and instruction,
使用 test-and-set 指令，
then, that lock, so the try lock will fail,
然后试着获取锁会失败，
and the the primary will add a message
primary 将添加一条消息
to the queue of the to the queue of the coordinator,
到协调者的队列中，
saying, like I you know I could not acquire the locks,
说，我不能获取锁，
and the coordinator in that case will abort transactions.
在这种情况下，协调者将中止事务。
Any questions so far?
到目前为止，还有什么问题吗？
How are the are the locks obtained, through zookeeper?
这些锁是如何获取的，通过 zookeeper 吗？
No, these are the other set of locks using zookeeper,
不，是另一套锁使用 zookeeper ，
that's really for configuration management,
是为了进行配置管理，
like the mapping of region number to primary and backups,
比如区域编号到 primary 和 backup 的映射，
these are just in memory locks, that the primary maintains,
这些只是内存锁，由 primary 维护，
so in the address space,
所以在地址空间中，
a little bit back, correct,
稍微向后一点，
little,bit back at this picture,
回到这张图片上，
there was a region has objects,
有一个区域有对象，
every object has some data and a header,
每个对象都有一些数据和头部，
and in that header, there's basically a 64 bit number,
在那个头部中，有一个 64 位编号，
that were top-level bit is the lock bit,
最高位是锁位，
and 63 other bits for the version number.
其他 63 位是版本编号。
Oh, what if the primary goes down,
哦，如果 primary 停机怎么办，
does the backup have the same locks of the primary?
backup 是否有与 primary 相同的锁？
If the primary goes down,
如果 primary 停机，
the whole, what's gonna happen is that,
接下来会发生的是，
there's a whole reconfiguration protocol,
有一个完整的重新配置协议，
happening in new recovery protocol,
在一个新的恢复协议中，
the end result of that is that,
其最终结果是，
in this case, the, we we hope that transaction would be abort, correct,
在这种情况下，我们希望事务会中止，
because it never made it to the end.
因为它不会到达最后。
We'll get to fault tolerance in a little while,
我们稍后会讨论容错，
so let's [] for,
所以让我们来，
I'm going to talk about in a couple boards,
我会再讨论几个白板，
and I'll talk about fault tolerance.
我会谈到容错。
Thank you.
谢谢。
So the version number are per object, right?
所以版本号是每个对象的，对吧？
Sure, per object, yeah.
当然，每个对象的，是的。
[].
[]。
Okay, good, so, alright.
好的，那么，好的。
Can I ask a question,
我能问个问题吗，
why do they choose to abort the transaction
为什么他们选择中止事务，
rather than blocking and waiting for the lock to be released?
而不是阻塞并等待锁被释放？
Because they have read old [material],
因为它们读到了旧的[材料]，
they have not read the latest material value,
它们没有读到最新的值，
and so the transaction has to abort.
所以，事务必须中止。
Oh I see,
哦，我明白了，
because the lock means that it's gonna change next time.
因为锁意味着下一次它会改变。
Well, they ask for locks after really written the object, right,
好的，它们在写完对象后才要求加锁，
so the coordinator modifies the object based on some version number,
协调者基于某个版本号修改对象，
submits a bunch of writes,
提交了一些写入，
assuming that is write the latest version number,
假设写入最新的版本号，
and so by the time the the commit starts happening,
这个时刻，提交开始，
and you try to get the locks,
然后你试图获取锁，
and you discover that somebody else is locked,
你发现另一个已经获取了锁，
that means somebody else already modifying it,
这意味着其他人已经修改它了，
and so that would violate serialization, right.
所以这会违反串行化。
Yep, thank you.
是的，谢谢。
So, in fact the point you get the lock here,
所以，你在这里得到锁的时候，
that's sort of the serialization point for write transactions,
这在某种程度上是写事务的串行化点，
at this point, the transaction has acquired all the locks,
在这个点，事务已经获取了所有锁，
for all the objects is modified,
对于所有被修改的对象，
so nobody else can actually modify in this particular point of time,
在这个时间点上，其他人都不能修改，
so that's sort of the serialization point for the write part of the transaction.
这在某种程度上是事务的写入部分的串行化点。
Make sense?
能理解吗?
Yes, thank you.
是的，谢谢。
Good okay, so now, you might have felt like,
好的，现在你可能会觉得，
why not do the same thing for read, correct,
为什么不对读取做同样的事情，
and you know get the lock for the read objects,
获取读取对象的锁，
get the lock from the objects that read,
从读取的对象中获取锁，
you know check the version number in you know in good [].
检查版本号[]。
And the reason that that is actually a separate phase,
原因是这是一个独立的阶段，
namely the validation phase
即验证阶段，
is to basically avoid these expensive write RDMAs, right,
是为了避免这些昂贵的写入 RDMA ，
if you look at this vertical step,
如果你看这个竖直的步骤，
you'll see there's a write RDMA,
你将看到有一个写入 RDMA ，
the server has to run something,
服务器必须运行一些东西，
basically does acquiring the locks,
基本上是获取锁，
and then responds with another write RDMA.
然后用另一个写入 RDMA 进行响应。
So here this is a full RPC,
所以这是一个完整的 RPC ，
that actually requires server participation,
需要服务器的参与，
and as we'll see in a second,
正如我们稍后将看到的，
in the, to handle the read the objects have been read,
为了处理对象已被读取，
the the the FaRM uses this validation step,
FaRM 使用这个校验步骤，
in the validation step, just used one-sided RDMAs,
在验证步骤中，仅使用了单边 RDMA ，
and so there's no real server involvement necessary.
所以，不需要真正的服务器参与。
Okay?
好的?
So, what happens on the,
所以，发生了什么，
so basically at this point, the where we here,
所以我们在这一点上，
the transaction coordinator actually has the write locks,
事务协调者具有写锁，
and now the only thing it does is,
现在它唯一做的就是，
it validates the read locks or basically read version numbers,
它验证读锁或读版本号，
and so it for every object that is read but not modified,
所以，对于每个已读取但未修改的对象，
so in our particular example,
在我们的示例中，
that's only one object,
只有一个对象，
this is the one that actually being read,
这是那个被读取的，
the one at region 3,
区域 3 的那个，
so it's, it basically is one-sided RDMA to read the version number,
所以它是单边 RDMA 读取版本编号，
that 64 bit number for the object is being read.
那个正在读取的对象的 64 位编号。
And when it gets back, when it gets back here,
当它回来这里的时候，
it checks two things,
它检查两件事，
if the lock is taken, so the lock bit set,
如果锁被获取，锁位被设置，
that means that some coordinator concurrent transactions is being, is trying to modified,
这意味着一些并发事务正在试图修改，
so that point just abort,
所以在这一点上，就中止，
and so the all the transaction abort again,
所有事务再次中止，
if the first number is identical and it's not locked,
如果第一个数字是[相同的]且未锁定，
that means that no other transactions using at this particular point of time,
这意味着在此特定时间点没有使用其他事务，
and the transaction could proceed,
事务可以继续进行，
basically all the objects that are being read and modified,
所有读取和修改的对象，
have the version number at the start of transaction,
在事务开始时具有版本号，
and nothing has changed yet,
一切都还没有改变，
and so it is okay for the transaction to commit,
所以，事务提交是可以的，
it is really the true serialization point.
它是真正的串行化点。
And since you know the transactions numbers
而且由于事务编号
are required at the beginning with version number,
在开始时需要版本号，
right at the beginning of the transaction,
在事务开始时，
you know the transaction will commit in the order of the version numbers basically,
事务将按照版本号的顺序提交，
and they also would get basically strict serializability,
它们将获得严格的可串行化，
because any transaction that will start after your transaction commits,
因为在你的事务提交后启动的任何事务
will have higher version number,
都将具有更高的版本号，
so therefore it also will commit later.
所以，它也会晚点提交。
Okay, so this is the point,
好的，这就是那个点，
basically where transaction coordinator says,
事务协调者说，
you know at this point you know the,
在这一点上，
we know that all the we have to, we have acquired the locks,
我们知道我们必须获得锁，
we have verified to validate the version numbers for the read objects,
我们已验证读取对象的版本号，
and so this is basically the commit point or the start of the commit point,
所以，这是提交点或提交点的开始，
so this point that is actually going to say,
所以这一点是在说，
okay, I'm gonna go, I'm gonna go commit.
好的，我要提交了。
And you know there's multiple messages necessary to commit point,
提交点需要多条消息，
we'll see in a second,
我们一会儿就会看到，
and those are mostly for fault tolerance reasons.
这些主要是出于容错的原因。
And so at this point,
所以在这一点上，
namely only the primary has been the,
只有 primary 已经，
only the primary have been contacted of the of the objects that are being modified,
只有 primary 已经联系正被修改的对象，
but not the backups.
但不包括 backup 。
And of course we want to ensure that and write,
当然，我们想要确保这一点，并写下，
you know once you commit will survive f failures, right,
一旦你提交，就能容忍 f 个故障，
system is designed to handle f+1 failures,
系统设计为处理 f+1 个故障，
in our particular designs, there's one backup,
在我们的设计中，有一个备份，
and so it can only survive one failure.
所以它只能容忍一个故障。
And so what happens in this final phase, commit backup phase,
所以发生在最后一个阶段，提交备份阶段，
is actually we're going to write to the logs of the primary of the backups,
是我们要写入备份的日志，
so the backups have log,
所以备份有日志，
so here's backup i,
所以这是 Bi ，
you know similar there's a log entry in it,
类似的，里面有一个日志条目，
and what we're gonna do is
我们要做的是，
write what's called commit backup record,
写下所谓的提交备份记录，
and the commit backup record exactly as the same information as the locking record,
提交备份记录与锁记录相同的信息，
that we saw earlier,
我们之前看到的，
so in it, is going to be the version number, the oid and the new value.
所以，它将包含版本号 oid 和新值。
Okay?
好的？
And this is you know like before this is actually done using write RDMA,
像之前一样，这是使用写入 RDMA ，
now the backup doesn't really have to do any operation at this point,
现在，备份在这一点上并不需要执行任何操作，
like the server side of the backup doesn't really have to run anything,
备份服务器端不需要运行任何东西，
just need and and so the the here's this trick,
所以这是这个技巧，
where basically the sender waits the acknowledgement of the NIC,
发送者等待网卡的确认，
and so this you know this is not one-sided or write RDMA,
所以这不是单方面的，也不是写入 RDMA ，
this is just make acknowledging that it got the write RDMA,
这只是确认它已获得写入 RDMA ，
and the write RDMA has been performed.
并且已经执行了写入 RDMA 。
And so that basically acknowledges,
所以，这是在确认，
you know when we get this particular point in the protocol,
当我们在协议中这一点时，
the transaction coordinator knows,
事务协调者知道，
the object is in the log of all the primaries,
对象在所有 primary 的日志中，
and objects in in the log of all the backups.
以及对象在所有备份日志中。
And so now we're in good position in terms of of fault tolerance, correct,
所以现在我们在容错性方面处于有利地位，
because if any one of the two fails,
因为如果两者中的任何一个失败了，
the other one can actually apply the write operation.
另一个可以应用写操作。
Then there's one more step that needs to be performed,
然后还有一个步骤需要执行，
and that is commit primary,
那就是提交 primary ，
I'll talk about a little bit later in more detail,
稍后我会更详细地谈到，
but this is the final step,
但这是最后一步，
where there's one more log record written,
更多日志记录写入，
in the primary, namely commit record,
在 primary 中，也就是提交记录，
and the commit record is is transaction id, that actually is being committed.
提交记录是正在提交的事务 id 。
So like every,
所以像每个，
I didn't write that down in the other records,
我没有把它写在其他记录里，
but every record has a transaction id,
但是每个记录都有一个事务 id ，
so we know which transaction we're talking about.
我们知道我们谈论的是哪一个事务。
And, again this use the same strategy,
同样，这也使用了相同的策略，
there's a write RDMA to appends, to the, to the log,
有一个写入 RDMA 要附加到日志，
and you know there's an acknowledgement, the NIC acknowledges the write RDMA,
有一个网卡确认写入 RDMA ，
and so but it doesn't require any interrupts,
但它不需要任何中断，
or there's no server itself is not being interfered with,
或者没有服务器，本身不受干扰，
just NIC is involved in these two operations.
只有网卡参与了这两个操作。
Then as soon as, one of the NICs acknowledges the commit record
一旦其中一个网卡确认提交记录，
on one of the primaries,
在一个 primary 上，
at that particular point of time,
在那个时间点，
which is actually really truly committed,
它是真正提交的，
so this is the true commit point,
所以这是真正的提交点，
the commit starts basically here,
提交从这里开始，
and this is actually the actual commit point,
这是实际的提交点，
at that particular point in time,
在这个特定时间点上，
the transaction coordinator informs the application,
事务协调者通知应用程序，
yes, your transaction has committed, and is done.
是的，你的事务已经提交，并且已经完成。
Then, of course some point later,
当然，稍后某个时刻，
the logs need to be cleaned and shortened up and truncated and all that kind of stuff,
日志需要清理、缩短和截断，诸如此类的事情，
and this is like the truncate phase,
这就是截断阶段，
and that's basically [] back on later locking phases and validation phases,
这是[]后面的锁阶段和验证阶段，
and so I'm not really going to talk about it at all,
所以我不会讨论它，
but basically they have to truncate the logs,
但是，它们必须截断日志，
so that they don't grow unbounded.
这样它们不会无限生长。
Sorry, but the hardware acts,
抱歉，硬件会起作用，
they just go directly into, into the NIC of the coordinator?
它们只是直接进入协调者的网卡？
Yeah, let's go back to the RDMA picture, right,
是的，让我们回到 RDMA 的图片上，
so if a write RDMA happens,
如果发生写入 RDMA ，
so here're write RDMA,
所以这是写入 RDMA ，
the sender coordinator was running here, right,
发送者协调者在这里运行，
and here's may be one of the primary, so the backups,
这可能是 primary 和 backup 之一，
and so the write RDMA goes in,
所以写入 RDMA 进入，
write maybe an entry to the log,
可能写入一个条目到日志中，
the NIC does that, NIC sends an acknowledgement back,
网卡发回一个确认，
and the coordinator will see that acknowledgment in the received queue,
协调者将在接收队列中看到确认，
and so soon as the coordinator sees the ack you know for it's write RDMA,
一旦协调者看到它的写入 RDMA 的 ack ，
it can proceed,
它可以继续，
and knows that the write RDMA succeeded.
并且知道写入 RDMA 成功了。
So does the write RDMA is only write to the log, they.
所以写入 RDMA 只是写入日志，它们。
They're used in two cases,
它们用在两种情况下，
they're both used for these message queues and for the the log append.
它们用于这些消息队列和日志追加。
And so when we say that a write RDMA has been performed,
所以，当我们说已经执行了写入 RDMA 时，
we mean that it has been appended to the log
我们的意思是它已被附加到日志中，
and not actually executed necessarily by the application.
并不一定由应用程序实际执行。
That's correct, that's correct,
对，对，
so for example you know to,
例如，
for example to the backup to actually perform the update to the object,
例如，备份执行对象的更新，
you need to read the log entry and then apply the update.
你需要读取日志条目，然后应用更新。
I see,
我明白了，
and also for the lock bit for every object,
还有每个对象的锁位，
so since everything resides in memory,
由于一切都驻留在内存中，
and we have like 64 bits for the version number plus the lock bit,
我们有 64 位的版本号加上锁位，
so I'm assuming that it can fit in a single memory address,
所以我想它可以放入一个单一的内存地址，
but we can still have the problem of,
但我们仍然会有这样的问题，
let's say the processor fetching that memory address into register,
假设处理器将该内存地址提取到寄存器中，
and then maybe if we have a multi-core machine,
然后，如果我们有一台多核计算机，
then another core fetching that that same address,
然后另一个内核获取相同的地址，
and then both of them flipping from 0 to 1,
然后它们都从 0 翻到 1 ，
so I'm assuming that there's some support from the hardware?
所以我假设有一些来自硬件的支持？
Yeah, so like I mentioned a bit earlier,
是的，就像我之前提到的，
the primary when it acquires,
当 primary 获取，
the primaries actually involved correct in the primary on,
primary 涉及到，
so the coordinator sends,
所以协调者发送，
so in the lock step like this, this step, step one,
所以在锁阶段，这个阶段一，
the primary or the coordinator sends an write RDMA to the to the primaries,
primary 或 coordinator 发送写入 RDMA 到 primary ，
asking the primaries to lock the object,
要求 primary 将对象加锁，
and the primaries answer explicitly with a message, then reply,
primary 用一条信息明确地回答，然后回复，
and so this crucial step that happens is,
所以发生的这一关键步骤是，
that the primary when it actually tries to get the lock,
当 primary 试着获取锁，
and that lock is set,
锁已经设置了，
you know reason this is one single 64 bit number,
这是一个单一的 64 位数字的原因，
is so that you can use [] test-and-set instruction,
是因为你可以使用 test-and-set 指令，
which is atomic to set the lock.
它是原子地设置锁。
So if two, so there's never the case,
所以，永远不会有这种情况，
there's only, if two test-and-set instructions run exactly the same time,
当两个 test-and-set 指令完全同时运行，
one is going to win, the other is going to lose.
一个会赢，另一个会输。
I see, thank you.
我明白了，谢谢。
That's a crucial point, right.
这是一个关键点。
I've got a question about the blue commit point.
我有一个关于蓝色提交点的问题。
Yeah.
嗯。
Wouldn't it, so.
它不会，所以。
Should I, let me,
我应该，让我，
maybe it's better to actually open a new slide with the picture again,
也许再打开一张带有图片的新幻灯片更好，
and just instead of scribbling even more over this,
不是在这个上面继续涂鸦，
I mean, let's get one more picture,
我是说，我们再来一张图，
so we can talk about other scenarios,
这样我们就可以讨论其他场景了，
I think a little bit bigger,
我想再大一点，
I think should do that.
我认为应该这么做。
Okay, so you're worried about,
好的，所以你担心的是，
let me see.
让我看一下。
Yeah, the commit point between step, after step 2, before step 3.
是的，那个提交点在步骤 2 和步骤 3 之间。
Yeah, so here, here's the decision, correct.
是的，这是[决定点]。
Right.
是的。
Starting to commit and then basically here's the actually commit point, right.
开始提交，然后是实际提交点。
Okay, yeah I guess I was trying to think about the scenario,
好的，我想我是在想这个场景，
where, would it be possible for a completely separate concurrent transaction,
对于一个完全独立的并发事务是否可能，
that writes only P3 to get interleaved,
只写入 P3 进行交错，
to like start and complete in that space,
在那个空间里开始和完成，
and then wasn't that?
然后这样不是？
No, [],
不，[]，
yeah, we're problematic, but can't, correct,
是的，我们有问题，但不能，
because when it writes,
因为当它写入时，
it does get the lock at some point,
它在某个点上获得锁，
and when we get the lock,
当我们获得锁时，
we check the version number and the lock bit.
我们检查版本号和锁位。
But, does the read, does the read the P3 affect the version number and lock bit?
但是，读取 P3 会影响版本号和锁位吗？
No, no, it just gets the version number.
不，它只获取版本号。
But if you, let let me hold that question,
但如果你，让我保留这个问题，
you're going to come back at this.
你会回到这个问题上。
Okay, then we'll see what actually happens?
好的，我们看看会发生什么？
Okay, thanks.
好的，谢谢。
Any other questions?
还有其他问题吗？
This might be like a separate scenario,
这可能像是一个单独的场景，
but what happens if you know after the execution phase,
但如果你在执行阶段之后，会发生什么，
you know it tries to acquire a lock,
它试图获取一个锁，
and then crashes right after that,
然后就在那之后崩溃了，
and the lock has been acquired,
锁已经被获取，
but no one else after that can acquire it.
但在那之后，其他任何人都无法获得它。
Yeah, okay, so well first of all, the machine disappears from the earth, correct,
是的，好的，首先，机器从地球上消失了，
and memory content is gone too,
内存内容也消息了，
and in the whole recovery protocol,
在整个恢复协议中，
that is described in the next section in the paper kicks in,
在论文的下一节描述的，
and that protocol in the end will abort the transaction,
协议最终中止了事务，
so it will get cleaned up.
所以，它将得到清理。
Just another question,
再问一个问题，
so here like the coordinator is the client, right, like it's the application.
所以这里协调者是客户端，就像应用程序一样。
Yeah, yeah.
是的。
And so the client is basically doing all the steps,
所以客户端做所有的步骤，
of like lock that.
比如 lock 。
Yeah, yeah, so you could think about
是的，所以你可以考虑
the applications running on the same set of 90 machines, right,
应用程序在 90 台机器上运行，
and you know running this transaction,
运行这个事务，
which apparently you know writes two objects and read one,
很显然，写入两个对象，读取一个，
and runs the protocol.
并且运行这个协议。
And so, I guess what's confusing is,
所以，我想令人困惑的是，
so does the primary not communicate with the backup directly, it's the.
所以 primary 并不直接与 backup 通信吗，它是。
No, it's actually indeed,
不，是这样的，
the primary does not directly communicate with the backup.
primary 不直接与 backup 通信。
I see.
我明白了。
Other than during recovery protocol,
除了在恢复协议期间，
there's all kinds of communication happening,
有各种各样的通信发生，
but that's not shown here.
但并没有在这里展示。
So the coordinator just uses the configuration from the zookeeper?
所以，协调者使用来 zookeeper 的配置？
Yeah, yeah, you go back to the very first picture,
是的，回到第一张图片，
you know there's all kinds of stuff you know related to this to that,
有各种各样的事情和这个有关，
I'm not talking about like this precise membership and all that kind of thing,
我不是在谈论，这种精确的关系之类的事情，
but basically the zookeeper and connection manager really decide,
但是由 zookeepr 和连接管理者决定，
well this is a configuration, the current configuration, we're running in,
这是我们运行的当前配置，
these are the regions,
这些是区域，
how they're mapped primary backups and all that stuff,
它们如何映射主备份和所有这些内容，
and in any failure happens,
在任何失败发生时，
you know there's a whole reconfiguration process going on and recovery.
有一个完整的重新配置进程并恢复。
I see, thank you.
我明白了，谢谢。
Okay, maybe I'm gonna skip the breakout room,
好的，也许我会跳过分组会议室，
and so I can go a little bit further,
所以我可以走得更远，
the question you know I wanted to answer the question,
我想要回答的问题，
that in the that was asking the post in the lecture,
在课程中贴出的，
I'm gonna lecture question,
课程问题，
and I'm just going to do that by talking about an example of transaction,
我将通过谈论一个事务的例子来回答，
and this also comes to the earlier question about,
这也涉及到之前的问题，
you know what happens,
会发生什么，
you know two transactions run and read one version,
两个事务运行并读取一个版本，
and then it commits blah blah blah all this stuff.
然后它提交了，等等，这些东西。
So so this is really the topic here
所以这是我们要讨论的话题，
is going to do we get strict serializability?
我们是否得到了严格的可串行化？
And what I'm gonna do is,
我要做的是，
I'm not going to give you proof you know that getting strict serializability will be,
我不会给你严格串行化的证据，
instead what I'm gonna do is,
相反，我要做的是，
I'm going to walk for one or two examples,
我来举一两个例子，
to get build up some intuition,
建立一些直觉，
and hopefully the intuition you know sort of convinced
希望直觉能让你确信，
you know that things might actually be fine.
事情可能是好的。
So let's look at the following transaction,
那么让我们来看下面的事务，
we have TxnBegin,
我们有 TxnBegin ，
and this transaction is,
这个事务是，
you know like in the beginning, it reads an object,
在一开始，它读取一个对象，
adds 1, and then write the object,
加 1 ，然后写入对象，
and commits or ends with commit by fail,
提交或以失败提交结束，
so that's a transaction.
所以这是一个事务。
And you know we want to ask yourself,
我们想问你自己，
what are the legal outcomes,
合法的结果是什么，
what are the outcomes correct.
正确的结果是什么。
So what are the possible outcomes of this transaction,
那么，这个事务可能的结果是什么，
what could be the state of,
会是什么状态，
let's say x started at 0,
假设 x 从 0 开始，
and we're running two transactions, you know T1 and T2,
我们运行两个事务， T1 和 T2 ，
what are the possible outcomes that are fine.
有哪些可能的结果是好的。
Either one of them could commit
它们中的一个可以提交，
or both of them could commit?
或者它们两个都可以提交？
Yeah, and so we can have x=2, correct, both commit,
是的，所以我们可以得到 x=2 ，两个都提交，
x=1, possibility one commit, and one another abort,
x=1 ，可能一个提交，另一个中止。
general two run concurrently or something,
一般是两个同时运行，
and any other possible outcomes?
还有其他可能的结果吗？
0.
0 。
Yeah 0,
是的， 0 ，
if you know basically both abort, right,
如果两个都中止了，
maybe there's a crash.
也许崩溃了。
Okay, so those are the three legal outcomes,
好的，这就是三种合法的结果，
so this, you have to make sure that is the case.
你必须确保是这样的。
So let's say T1 runs and so does a read operation,
假设 T1 运行，执行一个读取操作，
get x back, maybe at version 0,
将 x 从版本 0 取回，
same thing with T2, it reads you know x 0,
T2 也是一样，它读取 x0 ，
and so it's basically to run truly concurrent,
所以它是真正地同时运行，
and this is the question that we ask,
这是我们问的问题，
you know the lock question,
那个锁的问题，
we do lock x, we do lock x,
我们执行对 x 加锁，我们执行对 x 加锁，
and here sort of crucial step, correct,
这是关键的一步，
because at this particular point,
因为在这个时刻，
there we're trying to get the locks on object 0
我们试图获取对象 0 的锁，
and can both succeed?
两个都能成功吗？
In reading?
在读取中吗？
In getting the lock x.
在获取 x 锁的过程中。
Oh, in getting the lock,
哦，在获取锁的时候，
not at the same time.
不是在同一时间。
So one is gonna, one is going to succeed, correct.
所以一个会成功。
And so let's say the first one succeeds and gets the lock,
我们假设第一个成功，并获得了锁，
that means it can commit, right,
这意味着它可以提交，
so this guy will commit,
所以这个会提交，
and what happens with the second guy?
那个第二个会发生什么？
The second one, if it tries to obtain the lock at the same time,
第二个，如果它同时试图获取锁，
that the first one is holding the lock,
第一个持有锁，
it will abort and stop,
它将中止并停止，
if the first transaction goes through the way and the lock is released,
如果第一个事务通过并且锁被释放，
then it will obtain the lock,
然后它将获得锁，
and then check to see whether the version that it has for x is still correct,
然后检查 x 的版本是否仍然正确，
and it will find that the version has been changed,
它会发现版本已经被更改，
and then it will abort.
然后它会中止。
Yep, this is exactly the two, the two cases.
是的，是这两种情况。
So let me talk about validation case in in a second,
所以让我稍后来谈谈验证案例，
with a slightly different example, maybe more interesting,
使用一个稍有不同的例子，也许更有趣，
but this is basically the outcome, right.
但这就是结果。
Good, and so even though these transactions in this particular picture
很好，所以即使这张图中的事务，
run you know exactly at the same time,
同时运行，
they are actually getting ordered,
它们也是排序的，
and one wins and the other one loses,
一个赢了，另一个输了，
that means the other one that lost can run again,
这意味着另一个输了的可以再次运行，
it will then read Rx1 and then hopefully succeed in the retry.
然后它将读取 Rx1 ，然后希望在重试中成功。
Okay?
好的?
Okay, so.
好的，所以。
Okay, let me do one example,
好的，让我举个例子，
and then I'll stop and I'll resume on the on the Thursday,
然后我会停下来，在周四继续，
what time is it 24.
现在时间是 24 分。
Let me actually you know stop here,
让我停在这里，
and then I'll do second example,
然后我会做第二个例子，
that answers that earlier question,
回答前面的问题，
on on Thursday and also talk about fault tolerance,
在周四，也会讨论一下容错。
I don't want too much over time,
我不想超过太多时间，
anybody has to go, please feel free to go,
任何人必须离开，请随意离开，
and I'll see you in Thursday,
我们周四见，
anybody who asks, like to ask for more questions,
如果有人想问更多的问题，
you know please feel free to stay,
可以继续停留，
and I'll try the best to answer them,
我会尽最大努力回答它们，
as you see, this is a complicated paper,
如你所见，这是一篇复杂的论文，
and I'm glad that we're going,
我很高兴我们，
we're able to go and sort of depth and trying to really understand,
我们能够深入，并试图理解，
at least the protocol for normal operation.
至少是正常操作的协议。
So with that, I just like to finish this lecture,
说到这里，我想结束这节课，
and you know see you Thursday day
周四再见，
or if you have any questions, please hang around.
或者如果你有任何问题，请留下来。
I had two like the high-level questions,
我有两个高级别问题，
one was this, this whole hardware structure that they are using,
一个是，他们使用的这个整个硬件结构，
would it be useful at all,
它是否有用，
if you're using it with pessimistic concurrency control?
如果你将它与悲观并发控制一起使用？
Yes, I'm sure you can make the pessimistic protocol also better,
是的，我相信你也可以让悲观协议变得更好，
because you know RPC are just cheaper, right,
因为 RPC 更便宜，
but the real thing I haven't, I haven't been able to point this out yet,
但真正的东西，我还没能指出这一点，
but I was trying to,
但我试过了，
what I can do now,
我现在可以做，
is if you look at the read-only transactions here,
如果你看一下这里的只读事务，
so read-only transactions,
只读事务，
so if here transaction that basically the only reads an object or multiple objects,
如果这里的事务只读取一个对象或多个对象，
what's the performance, how good is that,
性能会怎么样，会有多好，
like how well is that gonna perform?
它的表现会有多好？
Probably pretty well, since you only do the one-sided.
可能很好，因为你只做单边的（RDMA）。
Yeah, correct, if you look at the object that is stored at region 3, correct,
是的，如果你看一下保存在区域 3 的对象，
which is the object that's being read,
它是被读取的对象，
the only thing that happens is one-sided reads or one-sided RDMA, correct,
唯一发生的事情是单边读取或单边 RDMA ，
and there's no writes, nothing at all,
没有写入，什么都没有，
so, those because of the this,
所以，因为这个，
because the read operation don't require locks,
因为读取操作不需要锁，
there's nothing to be written,
没有什么可写，
only thing that needs to happen is this validation step,
唯一需要做的就是这个验证步骤，
which also is one-sided RDMA,
也是单边 RDMA ，
so read-only transaction, you can just run with two one-sided RDMAs,
所以只读事务，你可以只使用两个单边 RDMA 运行，
and that's where the big win comes from
这就是好处的来源，
and the reason that point is there is,
而这一点的原因是，
because of the optimistic concurrency control.
因为是乐观并发控制。
So I think basically to exploit RDMAs [], []
所以我认为利用 RDMA []，
and I'm trying to make a read-only transactions really fast,
我试着让只读交易变得非常快，
they got went to optimistic concurrency control.
它们必须是乐观并发控制。
Okay, I see, I see, makes sense.
好的，我明白了，有道理。
Another question was about security,
另一个问题是关于安全的，
is this thing is gonna be secure, if it's,
这东西安全吗，如果它是，
I guess, someone already asked about this,
我想已经有人已经问过这件事，
but the part where the NIC just reads memory,
但是网卡读取内存的那部分，
it seems a little scary, so.
这看起来有点吓人，所以。
Yeah, it's totally scary,
是的，真的很吓人，
and so there's there's a bunch of interaction between,
所以，有一系列的交互，
you know when the RDMA connection is setup
当设置 RDMA 时，
the operating system and the application,
在操作系统和应用程序之间，
so the operating system won't allow the NIC to write to any arbitrary location,
所以，操作系统不允许网卡写入任何任意位置，
will tell it, you know here the addresses,
会告诉它，这里的地址，
here's the VM, virtual memory addresses, that you can write to.
这是你可以写入的虚拟内存地址。
Okay, so you can make that [].
好的，所以你可以让它[]。
Okay.
好的。
Exactly.
没错。
Question about the performance,
关于性能的问题，
so if you have, so the reads are quick,
所以读取是很快的，
because of the one-sided RDMAs,
因为单边的 RDMA ，
but if you have a lot of writes happening,
但如果你有大量的写入，
like a lot of data and contention.
比如大量的数据和争执。
Yeah.
是的。
So the case, or.
所以这种情况，还是。
No, correct, what happens if you have contention,
不，如果有争执会发生什么，
actually we saw this in this particular case, correct,
我们在这个案例中看到了，
yeah, if we have a lot of contention,
如果我们有很多争执，
one of the transaction will abort,
其中一个事务将中止，
so this is really you know good for transactions,
所以这是对事务有好处的，
that don't content or not writing to the same records or same objects.
不[]或不写入相同记录或相同对象。
And even the reads, right?
甚至是读取，是吗？
Yeah, even the reads,
是的，即使是读取，
because the version numbers may change.
因为版本号可能会改变。
So what's like the main, I guess use case for?
那么，我想主要的用例是什么？
There's a lot of, you know there's a lot of studies independent of this paper
有很多研究独立于这个论文，
about pessimistic versus optimistic concurrency control,
关于悲观与乐观并发控制，
and you know clearly from the two benchmarks,
从这两个基准中，
they use in the paper, like TPC-C and TATP,
他们在论文中使用的，比如 TPC-C 和 TATP ，
there's not a lot of conflicts,
没有太多的冲突，
so this is actually submitted maybe by different users or different clients,
所以可能是由不同的用户或不同的客户端提交的，
and they basically touch different [tables].
它们接触的是不同的[表]。
So I have a question,
我有一个问题，
if there's multiple clients doing transactions on the same object,
如果有多个客户端在同一对象上执行事务，
how, so they want to do a write RDMA, write to to the log,
它们想要执行写入 RDMA ，写入到日志，
is it possible that there would be conflict,
有没有可能会发生冲突，
like like one of them will write over the other log, or.
比如其中一个会重写另一个日志，或者。
No no, there's one lock per pair,
不，不，每对都有一把锁，
One lock per pair, okay.
每对都有一把锁，好的。
So every this exactly the reason why.
所以，这正是原因所在。
And and then, but in transactions like time,
然后，但是在事务中，比如时间，
is it like you know to provide serializability,
它是否提供可串行化，
is it time based on what?
时间基于什么？
On the version number.
基于版本号。
There's nothing like TrueTime or anything like that here,
这里没有 TrueTime 或类似的东西，
these logical numbers, like in same way as in lab 3,
这些逻辑编号，就像实验 3 中一样，
where you have logical sequence numbers,
你有逻辑编号，
for implementing your key-value store,
用于实现键值存储，
there's numbers basically played the same role.
这些编号起到了同样的作用。
Well, if two number of two transactions got the same number,
如果两个事务得到了相同的编号，
then only the one that got to the commit point first is going.
那么只有先到达提交点的那个才会。
Yeah, okay.
好的。
Yeah, this is this case, right,
是的，就是这个案例，
one abort, the other one succeed.
一个中止，另一个成功。
Okay.
好的。
If there is a message queue that is basically established between every pair,
如果在每一对之间建立了消息队列，
then how do you know,
那你怎么知道，
so then you have multiple message queues, given primary,
你将拥有多个消息队列，给 primary ，
how do you know which order to read those
你怎么知道读取这些东西的顺序，
and you don't read them out of order.
而且不会乱读它们的顺序。
There is, you read all the messages from one source in the same order, correct,
你以相同的顺序读取同一来源的所有消息，
because they're all gonna be in one queue,
因为它们都会在一个队列里，
so one source writes to one queue,
所以一个来源写入一个队列，
multiple machines like write you know concurrently to different queues,
多台机器同时写入不同的队列，
you don't know what the order anyway,
你不知道顺序是什么，
so it couldn't affect the correctness of the protocol.
所以，它不能影响协议的正确性。
I see, so we don't rely on the orderings of the incoming concurrent messages.
我明白了，所以我们不依赖于传入并发消息的顺序。
That's correct, you poll them in some order,
没错，你是按一定的顺序轮询的，
and then you poll the queues in some order,
然后你按一定的顺序轮询队列，
that's the way, that's the way that's going to be processed.
这就是要处理的方式。
Got it,
明白了，
also one more specific question,
还有一个更具体的问题，
there's a part where this is a paper, that provides lock lock-free reads,
论文中的一部分提供了无锁读取，
which we've just talked about,
也就是我们刚才谈到的，
but it also says, it also provides locality hints,
但它也表示，它还提供了本地线索，
which enable programmers to co relate related objects on the same set of machines.
使程序员能够将同一组机器上的相关对象相互关联。
Yeah.
是的。
And I do not understand that,
我不理解那个，
the latter part of the sentence.
句子的后半部分。
Okay, so I I have to look up the details what it is,
好的，我得查一下细节是什么，
but I think what you're referring to is that,
但我想你指的是，
if you, like if your objects are all kinds of different regions, correct,
如果你的对象在各种不同的区域，
like, let's look at this picture here,
比如，让我们看看这张图片，
then you would have to talk to lots of different primaries, right,
然后你必须和很多不同的 primary 进行交互，
so if you like object one is in this primary,
如果对象 1 在这个 primary ，
object two is in this primary,
对象 2 在这个 primary ，
and if you are touching many,
如果你接触到很多，
if you're touching always a cluster of objects together,
如果你总是接触一个集群的对象，
it would be nice, if that cluster of objects all at the same primary,
这是好的，如果所有对象集群都在同一个 primary 上，
so you only have to contact one primary instead of many.
所以你只需联系一个 primary ，而不是多个。
I see, thank you.
我明白了，谢谢。
Any further questions?
还有什么问题吗？
So this, so FaRM is not really suitable for long transactions, right,
所以 FaRM 不是很适合长的事务，
because because most.
因为大多数。
Yeah, you're worried long of transactions that you get conflicts.
是的，你担心长的事务会导致冲突。
I mean, it also is assuming, I guess read-only transactions,
我的意思是，我猜只读交易，
since we're really optimized for them, right.
因为我们为它们做了优化。
Yeah, absolutely,
是的，当然，
many transactions you know people done studies,
很多事务人们都在研究，
and you know you saw in Spanner paper too, correct,
你在 Spanner 论文上也看到了，
where a large fraction of the transactions are read-only transactions,
其中很大一部分事务是只读事务，
but that's clearly property of the workload.
但这显然是工作量所致。
I had, I think, going back to my earlier question,
我想回到我之前的问题，
I think I realized, I was misunderstanding [basic] about strict serializability,
我想我意识到，我误解了严格串行化的基础，
is it, so strict,
是不是，严格，
so okay, so here's here's a situation,
好的，这是一个情况，
say here's one transaction that begins first,
假设有一个事务先开始，
that writes shard 1, shard 2 and read shard 3,
它写入分片 1 ， 分片 2 以及读取分片 3 ，
and so that that begins like first time.
所以像第一次那样开始。
Write object.
写入对象。
Write 0.
写入 0 。
Write x 0, write y 0.
写入 x0 ，写入 y0 。
And then reads z.
然后读取 z 。
Okay, reads z0.
好的，读取 z0 。
And then say, there's this second transaction that begins after transaction 1 started.
然后，假设有第二个事务在事务 1 开始后开始。
You know like here?
比如在这里？
Yeah, and it writes z.
是的，它写入 z 。
So before before write z,
所以在写入 z 之前，
it must read z [].
必须读取 z 。
Yeah.
是的。
And so read z, what version number does it read?
所以读取 z ，它读取的版本号是什么？
The same, the same one to.
一样的。
And then say reads that tries to write z,
然后尝试写入 z ，
and then say T2 commits before T1 commits.
然后加入 T2 在 T1 提交之前提交。
Yes, okay, so this commits yep.
好的，所以这个提交。
And then T1 commits after T2 commits.
然后 T1 在 T2 提交之后提交。
We'll try to commit, correct,
我们试着提交，
now, we'll start doing this hold lock for validation blah blah blah, correct,
现在，我们将持有锁，为了验证，等等，
so before before, so what's gonna happen, correct,
所以什么会发生，
you know I was going to give you this example,
我要给你举这个例子，
this is an example that I'm saying for next lecture,
这是我在下一节课上讲的一个例子，
but, basically what happened z would be get,
但是发生的是， z 会获得，
z will get 1,
z 会获得 1 ，
at this point, the z will be a version of 1, correct,
在这一点上， z 是版本 1 ，
so the validation phase will run after the commit,
所以，验证阶段将在提交之后运行，
that's what you said.
这就是你说的。
Right.
是的。
And so here's a validation of z,
所以这里是对 z 的验证，
and you know it has 0, right,
它有 0 ，
and now it's 1 and will transaction will be abort.
现在是 1 ，事务将被中止。
Okay, so this is what I was wondering about that,
好的，这就是我想知道的，
so because after the validation phase passes,
因为在验证阶段过去之后，
there was a period of time,
有一段时间，
after the validation phase passes,
在验证阶段过去之后，
a period of time passes, it commits,
经过一段时间，它提交，
what if this validation happened before T2 committed,
如果验证发生在 T2 提交之前，
so it's still sort of old version number.
所以它仍然是旧的版本号。
It cannot happen,
这不可能发生，
because after the validation,
因为在验证之后，
after commit, after commit has completed, correct,
在提交完成之后，
the commit backup you know has recorded
提交备份已经记录，
and the primary have have made the change,
primary 必须做出改变，
before the application was returned,
在应用程序返回之前，
z has been updated.
z 已经更新。
Wouldn't, I guess what I'm saying is,
会不会，我想我要说的是，
isn't it possible for T1's validation phase to happen before
T1 的验证阶段是否有可能发生在，
or I guess maybe what I'm trying to say is,
或者我想说的是，
isn't it possible that T2's commit happens
是否可能 T2 的提交发生在，
between T1's validate, happens after T1 validate before T1's commit?
发生在 T1 验证之后提交之前？T1之后发生的情况在t1提交之前进行验证。
Clearly, you know there's a risk and must be excluded, and is executed,
显然，这是有风险的，必须排除，
so okay so you're worried,
所以，你是在担心，
let me construct this case,
让我来解释这个案例，
may we'll come back to in next week,
也许我们下周回来，
we're gonna talk it anyway,
我们讨论一下，
but I think you are worried about it,
但我觉得你担心的，
could get the picture back,
可以回到这张图片，
here here's, we did,
这里，我们做了，
so this guy committed,
这个提交了，
so you basically doing the commit phase,
所以你是在做提交阶段，
this is T1, after T2, actually T2,
这是 T1 ，应该是 T2 ，
so T2 is about doing is here, right,
所以 T2 在这里，
then T1 is coming in before everything happens,
然后 T1 在一切发生之前进来，
before the T2 is finished, correct.
在 T2 完成之前。
Right.
是的。
So like T1 validation also comes in here,
所以， T1 也从这里进来，
so maybe,
所以也许，
okay, let me rewrite it,
好的，让我重写一遍，
and I'll get back to you.
我会回复你。
Okay.
好的。
Exactly what I wanted to talk about.
这正是我想要谈的。
Okay, okay, thank you.
好的，谢谢。
So just make sure,
所以想确认一下，
you're asking about T2 being like in between stage two and three of T1?
你问的是 T2 在 T1 的第二阶段和第三阶段之间？
Yeah.
是的。
But in that case,
但在这种情况下，
then T2, we could, we could serialize it as T2 coming before T1, right.
我们可以串行化，让 T2 在 T1 之前。
Yep.
是的。
So, let's, let's get, let's get back to this on Thursday,
所以，让我们在周四回到这个话题上，
I have an example for that exactly was going to go over top of this.
我有一个例子可以说明这一点。
Sorry, in the validation stage, you just read, read the version number?
抱歉，在验证阶段，你只读取版本号？
Yeah.
是的。
Okay.
好的。
And serializability allows us to reorder transactions.
可串行化使我们能够对事务重新排序。
Yeah, but strict serializability will not, correct,
是的，但严格的可串行化不会，
if, if transaction, strict serializability requires that,
严格串行化要求，
if transaction actually starts, somebody, after somebody committed,
如果事务在某个提交之后开始，
that transaction is also committed after that transaction.
事务也要在那个事务之后提交。
Right.
是的。
Which is protocol guarantee,
这是协议保证的，
because of the, the version number.
因为版本号。
Got it, thank you.
知道了，谢谢。
But strict serializability doesn't,
但严格的可串行化不是，
if I get T2 ends,
如果我得到 T2 结束，
it's not refer T1 the end after T2 ends,
它不是 T1 在 T2 结束之后结束，
T1 have had to have started,
T1 必须已经开始，
or maybe I need to think about this,
或许我需要考虑一下这个问题，
but I think this is always tripping me out,
但我觉得这把我弄糊涂了，
this like there's also a rule about when the transaction starts.
这里也有一个关于事务开始的规则。
Yeah, well, well what happens in real life,
是的，好的，在真实生活中会发生什么，
exactly starts from some particular point of time,
准确地从某个特定的时间点开始，
and basically if T1, if T2 starts after T1 commits.
如果 T2 在 T1 提交后开始。
Right.
是的。
So and so then it must be the case,
所以，肯定是这样的，
that T2 observes you know T2 T1 changes,
T2 观察到 T1 的改变，
that's strict serializability.
这就是严格可串行化。
Right.
是的。
But what happened T2 starts and commits [] within?
但如果 T2 发生的[]，会怎么样？
Then concurrent transaction and either outcome is fine.
那么并发事务，任何一个结果都是好的。
Okay.
好的。
Is that answer your question?
这回答了你的问题吗？
Yeah, I think that I confused, so.
是的，我想这就是我困惑的，所以。
When they literally, when T2 starts before T1 commits,
确切地说，当 T2 在 T1 提交之前开始时，
it's considered the concurrent transaction,
它被认为是并发事务，
and so T1 or you know T2 can observe either,
所以 T1 或 T2 可以观察到彼此，
can be ordered before either after, doesn't matter.
可以排序在前或在后，没有关系。
Okay, okay.
好的，好的。
Okay, thank you.
好的，谢谢。
I think there's also the answer to your example.
我认为这也是你的例子的答案。
Right, okay, thank you.
是的，好的，谢谢。
Okay, we have we got it anyway already.
好的，我们已经得到了结果。
You're say if T2 started like between the T1 start and commit, right, like.
你是说，如果 T2 开始于 T1 开始和提交之间。
Yeah, you know, can be go for or after, it doesn't matter.
是的，可以在前面或后面，没有关系。
Can I ask a logistics question,
我能问个后勤问题吗，
I remember in 6.S081, you post these slides too.
我记得在 6.S081 ，你也贴了这些幻灯片。
Yes, I, yeah, yeah I didn't do that here,
是的，我没有在这里做，
would you like to be on the website?
你想它在网站上吗？
I think slides are useful,
我想幻灯片是有用的，
if if you just need to look at this slides,
如果你只需要看幻灯片，
you need to scroll through the video.
你需要滚动浏览视频。
Okay, you're first asking, why I haven't done it,
好的，你是第一个问的，为什么我没有这么做，
yeah, I'm happy to do it,
是的，我很乐意这么做，
I I do save them all.
我把它们保存下来。
Thank you so much,
非常感谢,
thank you for those fun lecture things.
谢谢你的有趣的课程。
You're welcome.
不用谢。